<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A glimpse of Gods glory: as it vvas presented in a sermon preached in St. Margarets Westminster, before the honorable House of Commons at the late solemne fast, September 28. 1642. By Tho: Hodges Rector of the Church at Kensington neere London. Published by order of that House.</title>
            <author>Hodges, Thomas, 1599 or 1600-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86432</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E124_36</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4544</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872698</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872698</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156167</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86432)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156167)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 22:E124[36])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A glimpse of Gods glory: as it vvas presented in a sermon preached in St. Margarets Westminster, before the honorable House of Commons at the late solemne fast, September 28. 1642. By Tho: Hodges Rector of the Church at Kensington neere London. Published by order of that House.</title>
                  <author>Hodges, Thomas, 1599 or 1600-1672.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. House of Commons.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 41, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Iohn Bartlet and are to be sold at the Gilt Cup in Pauls Church-yard neere S. Austins Gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXIII, 5-6 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156167:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A GLIMPSE OF GODS GLORY: AS IT VVAS PRESENTED In a SERMON preached in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. MARGARETS <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Before the Honorable Houſe of <hi>COMMONS</hi> At the late Solemne Faſt, <hi>September</hi> 28. 1642.</p>
            <p>By THO: HODGES <hi>Rector of the Church</hi> at Kenſington neere LONDON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Order of that Houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Iohn Bartlet</hi> and are to be ſold at the Gilt Cup in PAULS Church-yard neere S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Gate. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:156167:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156167:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable Houſe of COMMONS <hi>Now aſſembled in Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great God of Heaven and earth, who made what ever he made for his owne praiſe, hath ſtamped more excellent cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of his glory on man, then on all the reſt of his ſublunary creatures beſides: not onely making him Lord of all his works, but giving him underſtanding more then the beaſts; whereby, he might not onely be able like a earthly Monarch to rule over theſe earthly beings, but alſo might ſee in <hi>all</hi> his God, and thereby have his will inclined, and affections moved af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him, to know, and enjoy him, who is his eternall life. To this, man hath not onely an obliegement by commands, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits, and the like; but alſo by creation, an ability, and aptitude ſo to doe: But alas, how hath he loſt what he then received! and now like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> his ſpirituall eyes being gone, he is a ſtranger to the light of heaven, and all true liberty.</p>
            <p>And what is our miniſtery ſet up by this God in the world for? Is it not to turne poore undone men from darkneſſe to light, and from this ſpirituall bondage to the living God? But how ſhall we performe this taske, unleſſe by indeavouring ſo to bring this glorious God to light before them, that they may diſcerne what a glory they have ſleighted; and mourne, what a goodneſſe they have turned their back on, and change their mind; making for the future this God their end, and ayme in all their actions, and ſo make to their ſoules ſtraight ſteps toward the injoyment of him?</p>
            <p>We ſhall finde in Gods booke, that when Nations have overflowne with ſinne,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.1.6.</note> and conſequently with ruine as a juſt recompence and wages of it; it is attributed to the lack of
<pb facs="tcp:156167:3"/> this knowledge;<note place="margin">Eſay 11.9.</note> ſo on the other ſide, when the iniquitie of Kingdomes is deſtroyed, the knowledge of the Lord is laid downe as a meanes whereby it was brought to paſſe.</p>
            <p>This made me the rather pitch upon this ſubject, that this glimpſe of God might ſo affect our ſpirits, as not onely to fit us for that dayes duty wherein it was preached, but alſo for the future it might attract our minds unto him.</p>
            <p>The ſubject is high indeed, far ſitter for an Angels tongue, then for a mortall mans, eſpecially incompaſt with ſuch darkneſſe and infirmity as my ſelfe; which not being ſenſeleſſe of, had not your command ingaged the publication of theſe thoughts, they had never ſeene the light. But ſeeing your Wiſdomes have judged this meet; I ſhall ſit downe well pleaſed to have teſtified my obedience. Therefore I beſeech you, though the gift be far beneath your worth and eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, yet let the givers minde be accepted in it, which is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to any that prayes for your happineſſe, and deſires al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be found,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt humble ſervant</hi> in Chriſt Ieſus, <hi>THO: HODGES.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="Parliamentary_order">
            <head>Die Mercurii <hi>28.</hi> Septemb. <hi>1642.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the Commons Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that Mr. <hi>Hollis,</hi> and Sir <hi>Rob: Harley</hi> are appointed to returne thanks from this Houſe, to Mr. <hi>Hodges,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wilſon,</hi> for the great paines they have taken in the Sermons they prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched this day at S. <hi>Margarets</hi> Weſtminſter, at the intreaty of this Houſe. And that they deſire them to print their Sermons; And that no man preſume to print them, but ſuch as they ſhall appoint, untill the Houſe ſhall take farther Order.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſing Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I appoint <hi>Iohn Bartlet</hi> to print my Sermon.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Tho: Hodges.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:156167:3"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſad darkneſſe that covers Ireland, and many diſtractions of our own Kingdome, <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 12.12.</note> are God Almighties cals from heaven to the performance of this ſolemne duty. We are here therfore before the Lord this day, to lay our ſelves low before him; and <note n="b" place="margin">Hoſ. 12.4.</note> like <hi>Iacobs</hi> to wraſtle by prayers, and teares, with the great God, for the ſtopping theſe floods of wrath, which have made ſuch ſad breaches amongſt us; and to procure the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the one, and prevention of the like miſeries in the other Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The duty is extraordinary; But alas, we uſually bring ſuch ordinary hearts, that except the God of mercy be pleaſed to pity us, and raiſe us above our ſelves, the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is like to periſh in our hands, and we, to loſe that fruit which our ſoules deſire. Can we thinke that ſuch heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſpirits are like to procure the ſalvation of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes? Is not regardleſneſſe a thing in ordinary duties forbidden? nay, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the ſoul of God ſo much abhors, that he accounts the beſt works not to <note n="c" place="margin">Revel. 3.2.</note> fill up, where that is? Doth he not <note n="d" place="margin">Mal. 1.14.</note> curſe the deceiver, that offereth not the beſt, in the Old Law; and ſhall we think he will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of leſſe now? Therefore I beſeech you, let us not deceive our ſelves, but remember; As wee mete out to God, in the due performance of the duty of this <note n="e" place="margin">Luke 6.<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> day, ſo we may expect his meting to us again in the requeſts of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Alas, we are <note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 22.13.</note> very unapt to be drawne to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of duties of this nature, but if we take them in
<pb facs="tcp:156167:4"/> hand, wee are uſually ſo cold, ſo perfunctory, we care not which end goes forward, thinking a body <note n="g" place="margin">Eſay 58.5.</note> without a ſoule ſufficient, to diſcharge us of it; which doubtleſſe is amongſt divers other reaſons; becauſe, either we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not <note n="h" place="margin">Mal. 1.14.</note> how great a God we have to deale with in it, or expect not any great matter from the due perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of it; for, were we throughly convinced of the former, his glory would put us upon more diligent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertency; we would think <note n="i" place="margin">Revel. 4.8.</note> like the foure Beaſts, wee had need to have eyes both within and without, and all too little; and but for the latter, the poore cripples ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of an almes, or the Canaanitiſh womans of her daughters recovery, did not make the one more wiſhly <note n="k" place="margin">Acts 3.5.</note> to caſt an eye on the Apoſtle, <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 15.22.</note> or the other cry more fervently after our Saviour, then we would be, both to look, and cry, with attention, and fervour after the Lord this day, for that which is ſo affected by us.</p>
            <p>That therefore we may not be like the Dogs of <note n="m" place="margin">Aelian lib. <hi>6.</hi> de Animal. <hi>cap. 53.</hi>
               </note> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus, who running lap its waters; or like thoſe the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Eſay</hi> complaines of, <note n="n" place="margin">Eſay 54.7.</note> that ſtir not themſelves up to take hold of the Lord. Give me leave to preſent you this day with a glimpſe of what a God in this duty you have to deale with; How glorious, how able, how willing; That thereby your ſoules may be raiſed up to reverence, and attention, to hope, and confidence, to admiration, and elevation; Out of that portion of Scripture, contained in the hundreth and thirteenth Pſalme, the fift and ſixt verſes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156167:4"/>
            <head>A GLIMPSE OF GODS GLORY: As it was preſented in a SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSALME 113.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VERSE 5.</hi> Who is like unto the Lord our God, who dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth on high?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VERSE 6.</hi> Who humbleth himſelfe to behold the things that are in heaven, and in the earth?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author of this Pſalme was <hi>David;</hi> the time, when hee came newly to the Crowne;<note place="margin">Iun. et Tremel. Annotat. in loc.</note> The matter, praiſe;
<list>
                  <item>1. To God.</item>
                  <item>2. Of God.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Both joyned in this Text.</p>
            <p>In which obſerve Gods
<list>
                  <item>1. Majeſty.</item>
                  <item>2. Mercy.</item>
                  <item>3. The impreſſion this maketh on the Pſalmiſt.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Gods Majeſty, expreſt by,
<list>
                     <item>1. His eminency, hee is <hi>on high;</hi> and that is farther diſcovered by the Originall and fountaine of it, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, He exalts himſelfe on high, ſo the word ſignifies.</item>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:156167:5"/>
                     <item>2. By the immutability, and eternity of it; He <note n="*" place="margin">
                           <hi>R. Maim. Mor<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Nevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim.</hi> l. 1. c. 11.</note> 
                        <hi>fits,</hi> or <hi>dwels</hi> on high.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Gods mercy, which appeares, in His
<list>
                     <item>1. Providence.</item>
                     <item>2. Relation.</item>
                     <item>3. Condeſcenſion.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. His providence: In that obſerve, The
<list>
                           <item>Act, he <hi>beholds.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Object, and that is double;
<list>
                                 <item>1. Things in Heaven.</item>
                                 <item>2. Things on earth.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. In his exhibiting himſelfe by way of Relation, <hi>He is our God.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. In his great <hi>condeſcenſion;</hi> though he be ſo high, yet for the preſervation, and gubernation of his poore creatures, hee <hi>abaſeth</hi> himſelfe; <hi>i. e.</hi> rather then they ſhall want governing and ſuſtaining, hee will take charge of them himſelfe, and ſo far vaile his glory, as to imploy his wiſdome, power, and other attributes for their advantage.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. The impreſſion that this apprehenſion makes on the minde of the Pſalmiſt, and that is <hi>Admiration: O who is like unto him!</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Gods <hi>eminency; He is on high:</hi> Therefore ſtiled by the <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 57.15.</note> Prophet, the <hi>High and lofty one;</hi> and ſo he is indeed:</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of place and dwelling; <hi>He is in Heaven,</hi> ſayes <note n="b" place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon;</hi> and our Saviour in our prayers inſtructs us to looke up <note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 6.</note> thither. It is true, he is in the aereall, and Starry heaven by his eſſence and power; But the Heaven of the bleſſed is his <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 66.1.</note> 
               <hi>Throne,</hi> that is the place where he chiefly teſtifies his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence; not as if he were determined ſo to that place, as to be excluded from others; <note n="e" place="margin">1 Kings 8.27.</note> 
               <hi>The heaven of heavens is not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine him, for</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 23.24.</note> 
               <hi>he fils both heaven and earth;</hi> but in reſpect of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation he is ſaid to be there, becauſe in that place he chiefly manifeſts <note n="g" place="margin">Eſay 63.15.</note> his glory and goodneſſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect of <hi>eſſence,</hi> he is high indeed, unexpreſſibly high in excellency above all beings, not <note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 14.22.</note> onely in <hi>Abrahams</hi> phraſe, <hi>The high God,</hi> but in <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 7.17.</note> 
               <hi>Davids, The Lord moſt High.</hi> Alas, what are all created beings with all their excellencies in reſpect of him, but even as <note n="k" place="margin">Eſay 40.17.</note> 
               <hi>nothing</hi> and <hi>vanity,</hi> as the Prophet
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156167:5"/> ſpeakes? <hi>He is the perfecteſt of all Beings.</hi> For firſt, there's no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in any created being (if it be not <hi>a helpe of its neceſsitie, or a remedie againſt the evill that is incident to it)</hi> but we may finde it all in God. Is it <note n="l" place="margin">Jer. 10.10.</note> 
               <hi>life,</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>knowledge,</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Job 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>strength,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Lev. 11.44.</note> 
               <hi>holineſſe,</hi> or what ever elſe is <hi>ſimply excellent?</hi> he is the Originall and cauſe of all: therefore much more poſſeſſes theſe excellencies then the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 94.9.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they are all in God after a <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Dionyſ. de divi. nominibus c. <hi>1.</hi> Sic Aquin. parte <hi>1.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> art. <hi>1</hi> &amp; <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> ſuper-eminent man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>For, 1. they are divers things in the creatures, but one in God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They are accidents in the creatures, but eſſence in God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They are in the creature with ſome allay or other, they are like the moone, when they ſhine brighteſt, yet there are <hi>creature ſpots of imperfection</hi> to be found in them: <note n="r" place="margin">Job 4.18.</note> the Angels the excellenteſt of created Beings, are charg'd with folly. But God is <hi>ſo light That in him there</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">1 Joh. 1.5.</note> 
               <hi>is no darkeneſſe at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then thirdly, in reſpect of meaſure, he is infinitely above them all. Alas, they poſſeſſe but ſome ſmall drops in reſpect of the fountaine, ſome poore glimmering rayes in reſpect of this glorious ſunne; in a word, He is an <hi>infinite Ocean of perfection, without either brinke, or bottome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. He is high in reſpect of <note n="t" place="margin">Rab. Maymon. in more Nevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chim lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>State,</hi> and <hi>dominion.</hi> Looke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all thoſe that he is pleaſed to grace with the Title of gods, whether Angels in heaven, or men upon earth, and you will finde, <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 86.8.</note> 
               <hi>That amongſt the gods, there's none like unto him, neither are there any workes like unto his workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, looke upon all the gods; who amongſt them hath the <note n="w" place="margin">Eſay 66.1.</note> 
               <hi>whole heaven for his throne, and the whole earth for his footeſtoole,</hi> as he hath? <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 95.3, 4, 5.</note> who hath ſuch vaſte territories and dominions? <note n="y" place="margin">Eſay 33.22. Jam. 4.12. Rom. 9.21. &amp;c.</note> who ſuch ſupreame power and abſolute authoritie? <note n="z" place="margin">Revel. 19.16.</note> he is the <hi>God of gods, and King of kings;</hi> there's never a reſembling or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted God amongſt them, but they are beholding to him for <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.7.</note> their glory; it is their height &amp; honour to be the <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 82.6.</note> 
               <hi>Sonnes of the Higheſt:</hi> if they be higher then others in place, or parts, it is from his coyning, they paſſe with others at ſuch a rate. And as the putting forth of his creating power made them ſuch, ſo his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie is the <hi>meaſure</hi> of theirs: the nigher they come to him in point of likeneſſe or imployment, <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 16.3. Prov. 12.26. Dan. 4.36.</note> the higher they are in point of eminencie.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:156167:6"/>
            <p>Looke upon his workes, and he is high in them too; <hi>there is none amongſt the gods, whoſe workes are</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 86.8.</note> 
               <hi>like to his,</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 40.5.</note> they out-paſſe expreſſion. View this, 1. In the workes of Creation: <note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 40.12.</note> 
               <hi>Who hath meaſured the waters in the hollow of his hand, and meted out heaven with the span, and comprehended the duſt of the earth in a meaſure, and weighed the mountaines in ſcales, and the hills in a bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance?</hi> Are not theſe high workes indeede, thus to forme and proportion out ſuch vaſte creatures, and that with ſo much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilitie, and eaſe (as the Prophet expreſſes) with ſuch unexpreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſurpaſſing power, as if he were but ſpanning; meaſuring, weighing; can any leſſe then a high Almighty Deity doe it? Princes declare their highneſſe, by high extraordinary workes; <note n="g" place="margin">Dan. 4.30.</note> 
               <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> builds a glorious palace, to diſcover his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, and great glory; but alas, what is this poore pile to <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 33.6. Pſal. 102.25.</note> the <hi>laying of the foundations of the earth, and the creating the glorious fabricke of the vaſt heavens? which are alſo the worke of his hands.</hi> If we contemplate all theſe creatures, firſt, in God, before they had a Being in themſelves; <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 139.16. <hi>Plato</hi> ſtiles God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> as the <hi>Idea,</hi> or <hi>ſhape</hi> of the worke in the Artificers minde, before he puts his hand to frame it; ſo all creatures were in the divine underſtanding: and here for the farther extolling his heigth, we may well cry out with the <note n="k" place="margin">Eſay 40.13.14.</note> Prophet, <hi>Who hath directed the Spirit of the Lord? or being his counſellor taught him? with whom tooke he counſell?</hi> But all this while he was like <note n="l" place="margin">Ante omnia Deus erat ſolus ipſe ſibi &amp; mundus, &amp; lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, &amp; omnia, Tertul. coat. Prox.</note> 
               <hi>a claspt booke,</hi> gloriouſly ſhining onely to himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, looke alſo upon him in his creating <hi>emanations;</hi> this glorious booke is unclaſpt, and now what was hidden be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in God becomes manifeſt; ſo that thereby <note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 1.20. Pſa. 104.30, 31</note> 
               <hi>the inviſible things of God from the Creation of the world are clearely ſeene, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternall power and God-head;</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Eſth. 1.4.</note> like <hi>Ahaſueroſh</hi> his great feaſt, whereby hee ſhewed <hi>the greatneſſe of his riches and excellencie:</hi> And indeed what are the creatures, but the <note n="o" place="margin">Quid eſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellentia crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae, niſi Dei exundatio, qua inferiora etiam replevit? Bern.</note> 
               <hi>Over-flowings</hi> of Gods power, and eminencie; whereby not contenting himſelfe with diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries of his highneſſe, and glory in the creation of the heavens, and their glorious furniture of Angels, Sunne, Moone, Starres, and ſuch like, he hath likewiſe repleniſht the earth, <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 33.5, 6. Eſay 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>which alſo is full of his goodneſſe, and glory?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, as all things flow from him, ſo they depend
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:156167:6"/> upon him; which likewiſe declares his Highneſſe. The grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt excellencies of Being, or indowments which we ſo much admire, as <hi>wiſedome, ſtrength, life, holineſſe, &amp;c.</hi> as much depend upon him, as the <hi>effigies in the glaſſe upon the preſence of the face that cauſes it:</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 104.29.</note> 
               <hi>If he turne away his face i. e.</hi> reſtraine his influence, of ſuſtaining, maintaining grace, and power, <hi>they vaniſh.</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 1.3.</note> He ſuſtaines, and beares up all, both in reſpect of <note n="s" place="margin">Act. 17.28.</note> 
               <hi>being, excellencies, and operations.</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 104.27.</note> He maintaines, and ſpreads a table for all, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hither they looke with a <hi>craving, imploring eye:</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 107.</note> eſpecially in dangers, they that deſpiſe his majeſtie before, now acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge his highneſſe above all others; for, forſaking their fellow creatures, which are <hi>refuges of lyes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Non ad capito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, ſed ad coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, &amp;c. Tertul</note> they looke now to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, not to the Capitol: And thoſe that would not owne him before, cry now, Lord helpe, Lord ſave, lowdly thereby pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming his glory.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he to whom all <hi>tend</hi> muſt needes be on <hi>high;</hi> but as all came from him, and live upon him, ſo they <note n="w" place="margin">Rom. 11.36.</note> tend to him, as <note n="x" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.7.</note> 
               <hi>rivers which come from the Sea and returne againe unto it.</hi> When he framed all, firſt the end he aymed at <note n="y" place="margin">Deus in exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riora quídem tendit, ſed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in totum undi<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> in ſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Senec. lib. de beata vita, cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> was <hi>himſelfe,</hi> his own <note n="z" place="margin">Prov. 16.4.</note> 
               <hi>glory,</hi> for which he accordingly <hi>Stampt</hi> them with ſuch ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall adaptations, as might without faile, diſpoſe them for, and carry them to this end. Some tend to him, and ſo praiſe him paſſively, as the excellencie of the worke extolls the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 19.1.</note> Thus <hi>the heavens declare the glory of God, and the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhewes forth his handy worke.</hi> Likewiſe the Acts of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, both of Juſtice and Mercy, when by an <hi>out-ſtretched</hi> arme he reduces thoſe <hi>creatures,</hi> and <hi>things</hi> into order in relation to this end, which otherwiſe in themſelves would prove irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 76.10.</note> Thus he makes the <hi>wrath of man to praiſe him:</hi> as <hi>Pharaohs,</hi> when not onely thereby he tooke occaſion to ſhew how much he was <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 18.11.</note> 
               <hi>above</hi> him, and higher then he, by blaſting his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, enervating his courage, deſtroying his power; But alſo, when he had permitted that beaſt to rage <hi>enough,</hi> to bring about his owne deſigne, <hi>The remainder of his wrath</hi> (as the Pſalmiſt ſpeakes) <hi>God did ſubdue,</hi> by making the ſea his grave. The like we may ſee in <note n="d" place="margin">Socrat. Schol. Eccleſ. Hiſt. li. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Julian,</hi> if we conſider his bloody reſolutions, fierce proſecution, but ſuddaine and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous deſtruction: the like is evident in the King of <note n="e" place="margin">Eſay 10.</note> 
               <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> and many others.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:156167:7"/>
            <p>Others tend to him <hi>Actively</hi> by way of <hi>intention;</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 24.6.</note> propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this high God to themſelves as there <hi>ultimat</hi> end, and aym.</p>
            <p>They looke up to him as the <hi>onely One,</hi> in injoyment of whom they can be perfected: Therefore move towards him as their <note n="g" place="margin">Domine ſeciſti nos ad te, &amp; inquietum eſt cor noſtrum dónec requieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat in te, Aug. conf. l. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Sy<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. hymno <hi>2. Pſa. 73.25.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſal. 63.8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Center,</hi> and cannot finde quietnes in themſelves, <hi>untill,</hi> and <hi>no farther</hi> then they reſt in him. Their wiſh is, <note n="h" place="margin">Vt currat vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta mea in am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexus tuos, nec avertetur donec abſcondit me in abſcondito vultus tui. Aug.</note> that they may by every act and duty they performe, be thereby carryed into his imbraces, and never leave off, till at laſt they be ſwallowed up of his unſpeakeable glory.</p>
            <p>Thus whether we conſider Gods <hi>Eſſence, Dwelling, Dominion,</hi> or <hi>workes,</hi> we ſee in all he is <hi>High.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But how <hi>high</hi> is he?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. So high, that all creatures bow before him, and doe homage to him according to their ſeverall <hi>aptitudes</hi> and abilities. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> brings them all in, attributing to him, and ſo putting from themſelves, but ſetting on his head, as a royalty due onely to him, the crown of glory: <note n="i" place="margin">Revel. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>And every creature</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which is in heaven, and on earth and under the earth, and ſuch as are in the ſea, and all that are in them, heard I ſaying, Bleſſing, honour, glory, and power be unto him that ſits upon the throne.</hi> 1. Some by way of ſubjection, ſtooping to him, <note n="k" place="margin">Dan. 7 10. Rev. 5.11, 12.</note> Angels, and Saints they worſhip him, acknowledging his highneſſe, by denying their own,<note place="margin">Eſay 6.</note> but ſetting up his will as their ſupreame law &amp; excellencie, caſt down their crowns, and vayling their glory, they cover their face, and make his glory the object of their admiration. 2. Others acknowledge his eminencie by their <hi>Conſternation</hi> upon the leaſt ſhining forth of his glory, when he diſcovers but the emblems of his greatneſſe, <note n="l" place="margin">James 2.19.</note> 
               <hi>Devils tremble,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Eſay 33.14.</note> 
               <hi>Men quake;</hi> and as the wormes when it thunders wriggle into the corners of the earth; ſo, for all mens lofty lookes, though when all is quiet, they may puffe up themſelves with conceite they are ſomething more then or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, like <note n="n" place="margin">Sueton. in Calig.</note> 
               <hi>Caligula,</hi> who fancied himſelfe a God imitating <hi>Ioves</hi> thunder: But when the true God gave forth this voyce of his Majeſtie from heaven, he that before was ſo high, was now as low, and poore in his Spirit, covering his eyes with his cap, running under the bed, or into any bench-hole for preſervation; ſo let but the Lord ariſe to <hi>ſhake the earth terribly,</hi> and the talleſt Cedar, the higheſt tower, the loftieſt ſpirit of godleſſe men, can dare it no longer, but will thinke the <note n="o" place="margin">Eſay 2.19.</note> holes of the rockes, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156167:7"/> caves of the earth to be their beſt fence and ſhelter.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, even inanimate creatures by <note n="p" place="margin">Hab. 3.9, 10, 11. Eſay 48.13. Dan. 4.3.5.</note> 
               <hi>compliance</hi> with, and ready ſubjection to, the <hi>impreſſions</hi> of his power: <note n="q" place="margin">Job. 38 35.</note> the lightnings flye, the right ayming thunderbolt makes ſpeed at his direction, the beſt impreſſion of his power; if he doe <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 144 5.</note> but <hi>touch</hi> the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines they ſmoake, and the hills tremble: <note n="s" place="margin">Nahum 1.4, 5, 6.</note> But if he be angry he rebukes <hi>the ſea, and rivers they dry up; Baſhan, Carmel, Lebanus, languiſh,</hi> the mountaines quake at him, the hills melt, and the earth is burnt up at his preſence yea the world and all that dwell therein; Who may endure in his indignation? alas, none may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him, his wrath is ſo high, ore-topping the creatures weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that it is all one whether it be againſt a man or againſt a <note n="a" place="margin">Job 34.29.</note> Nation. 2. He is ſo high that he ſurmounts all created capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie to comprehend him. <hi>Canst thou</hi> (ſaith <note n="b" place="margin">Job 11.7, 8, 9</note> 
               <hi>Zophar</hi> the <hi>Naama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thite</hi> to <hi>Job) by ſearching finde out God? canſt thou finde out the Almighty to perfection? It is as high as heaven, what canſt thou doe? deeper than hell, what canst thou know? the meaſure thereof is lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then the earth, and broader then the ſea.</hi> So that indeede in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> phraſe, his greatneſſe and eminencie is <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 145.3.</note> 
               <hi>unſearchable.</hi> This that heathen Philoſopher <note n="d" place="margin">Mau<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>i. Loc. com.</note> 
               <hi>Simonides</hi> well expreſt when being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by <hi>Hiero</hi> the Tyrant to tell him, <hi>what was God,</hi> he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for ſolution, firſt one dayes reſpite, but at the end of that two, when they were expired foure, ſtill doubling his time for inquirie; till at the laſt being by the demander askt the reaſon of his delayes, he told him plainly; that by how much the more he thought of God, by ſo much the more he apprehended the impoſſibility of declaring what he was. In a word; he is ſo high, 1. That no bodily eye hath ever, <note n="e" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.12.</note> or can poſſibly ſee him. Therefore if we read of <hi>Abraham, Moſes, Eſay, Ezekiel,</hi> or others, of whom the contrary ſeemes to be aſſerted, we muſt underſtand it thus: that indeede they did ſee <note n="f" place="margin">R. Maymon. more Nev<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chim. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mercavah ve lo Harocheh, i. e.</hi> the Chariot in which God road, but not the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in it; they ſaw ſome created image, glory, whereby he was pleaſed for the preſent to teſtifie his more immediate preſence, but not himſelfe. 2. Neither can the eye of the Underſtanding perfectly reach. He dwels in ſuch <hi>inacceſſible light,</hi> that no mortall eye can attaine to; nay, (but through vailes, and clouding, yet proportionating mediums) get the leaſt glimpſe of; and that not by direct view of God in himſelfe, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156167:8"/> (as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> expreſſes it well) as weake eyes gaze not on the ſunne in its Orbe,<note place="margin">Nazianz. <hi>1.</hi> Theol.</note> that's to bright, but on its reſemblance in the water; ſo we on God in his Word, and workes, in, and upon which he hath left ſufficient manifeſtations of his eminencie, to attract our ſpirits, lay low our lofty mindes, and make us live by the apprehenſion of them: yet muſt we not thinke, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by his mercy we reach ſome little glimmering beame of his infinite unexpreſſible highneſſe thus (as it were) at the ſecond hand, that therefore we either doe, or can by any meanes ever be able perfectly to meaſure his highneſſe; which no created line, or underſtanding can ever doe, no not angelicall, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo vaſt a diſtance betweene an infinite glory, and a finite ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie. We ſee indeede, the eye of our body may be fill'd with the ſun brightneſſe, but it is impoſſible that ſo narrow a receptacle ſhould perfectly containe ſuch a large glory: So, although the Angels underſtandings now are, and the Saints, hereafter ſhall be fil'd brimfull with the cleare manifeſtations of Gods emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie and glory, yet that they can fully reach, or perfectly containe the exact, and preciſe knowledge of it, is an errour ſo groſſe, that it much more deſerveth pity then confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>If he be ſo high, that no created line can meaſure him, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Angels now, or Saints hereafter: alas, how much leſſe can we dream of doing it here? Conſidering likewiſe (which far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſcovers his eminencie) he is ſo high, that, 1. He ſurmounts all creatures, he hath no parallel. 2. <note n="g" place="margin">Iſta de Deo di cimus, quia non invenimus melius quod di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus, &amp;c. Aug. Serm. <hi>40.</hi> de Tempore.</note> Surpaſſes all notion. 3. <note n="h" place="margin">Vide Nazia. Orat. <hi>36.</hi> Afri vocant Deum ignotum Amon, i. e. Heus tu quis es? Plu. lib. de I ſide &amp; O ſir.</note> Is above all name. When <hi>Manoah</hi> inquires after his name, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is, Tis Wonderful, <hi>i e.</hi> I am cal'd as I am cal'd; but ſuch is thy weakeneſſe, that it ſurpaſſes thy conception: ſo <hi>Bede, Victorinus,</hi> and others on <hi>Exodus</hi> interpret it. 4. He muſt needes therefore be beyond the tongues expreſſion, if he be above the mindes apprehenſion; and ſo indeede he is incomprehenſible by the mind, unexpreſſible by the tongue, as <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Syneſ.</note> 
               <hi>Syneſius</hi> ſpeakes.</p>
            <p>To cloſe this Doctrine; he is indeede like the poole <note n="k" place="margin">Ariſtot. de mirabil. auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</note> 
               <hi>Polycritus</hi> writes of, cited by <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> which in compaſſe at the firſt ſcarce ſeemed to exceede the breadth of a ſhield, but if any went into it to waſh, it extended it ſelfe ſtill more and more: ſo is it with Gods glorious excellencie, which though at the firſt to a carnall eye it appeares but ſmall, yet the more the mind
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:156167:8"/> is exerciſed about it, the larger it ſhewes, till at the laſt it proves <note n="l" place="margin">Tantum rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit quantum capitur, Nazia. Oratione pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</note> incomprehenſible, and the underſtanding be ſwallowed up by it.</p>
            <p>Now let us come to the application of this truth, wherein I ſhall onely ſpeake of what I conceive may be moſt appoſite to further us in the preſent duty of this day, and of moſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to our ſelves here preſent.</p>
            <p>And here firſt, we may juſtly take up a ſad complaint, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God is ſo high, we ſhould be ſo unworthy to bring him ſo low and debaſe him as we have done. Have not we given him juſt ground to put that queſtion to us (or rather complaint) <note n="m" place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. 1. We have brought God low.</note> Where is my honour? Where is it indeede? unleſſe it conſiſts in giving him, 1. Onely <note n="n" place="margin">Eſay 29.</note> a body without a ſoule: as if he were not the God of both, or would be ſatisfied with the one without the other, or did not deſerve both. 2. Or if the beſt part, yet in that the worſt, and loweſt place,<note n="o" place="margin">Qui totum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, habere cum communem cum adverſario non dignatur, Greg. Magn.</note> as if ſome empty peece of vanity did better deſerve the throne, then the God of glory. See it in thoſe two ſtrong paſſions onely of love, and feare. Alas, firſt in our love, and eſtimation, doth not the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous perſon ſet up his gold above his God? the ambitious his honour? the uncleane perſon his harlots, thoſe unhappie ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of publike luſt, as <note n="p" place="margin">Infaeliciſſimas publicarum li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hidinum victi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Tertul.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſtiles them? and in truth, every one without Gods grace, his will, with a little inverting the Prophets phraſe, we may truely ſay, that <note n="q" place="margin">Jer. 11.13.</note> according to the number of their luſts and humors ſo are their gods. <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Heſiod.</note> 
               <hi>Heſiod</hi> ſayes there are thirty thouſand. And the ſpirit of the <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> was ſo low, that the meaneſt creature was good enough to make a god of; the truth is, there is nothing ſo meane that a carnall heart will not Idolize, and advance in affection above the Higheſt; if it bear a proportion to it ſelfe, it will make a god of it. Not by externall adoration, that's too groſſe, but by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall affection, and beſtowing the heart upon it, which is as reall a ſetting up a falſe God, though not ſo palpable, as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. But perhaps becauſe like <hi>Iſraels</hi> Elders in <note n="c" place="margin">Ezek. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> men act this privately, they will deny it, and pleade not guilty: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that we may no longer ſhift this off, but receive convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of it, conſider for diſcovery theſe three things. Firſt, which way runnes the current of our thoughts? ſpend we not more? dwels not our hearts longer, and that too with greater content
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156167:9"/> on other objects, then on God? Remember our Saviours rule: <note n="s" place="margin">Mat. 6.21.</note> Where the treaſure is, there will the heart be alſo. Secondly, have not other things a ſtronger influence into our actions then God, we will doe more for them then him; for did not riches intice, honours provoke, pleaſures allure, it is much to be feared that moſt would (command God what he pleaſe) prove uſeleſſe, inactive, burdens to the earth that beares them. Nay doe we not ſee the prevalencie of theſe? for what is it moſt men will not doe to gaine them? forgoe faith, and truth, Religion and piety, as <note n="t" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.10.</note> 
               <hi>Demas</hi> who forſooke his miniſtery, becauſe he ſaw it was no thriving way, and went to <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Doroth in Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopſ.</note> there turning Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous Prieſt: <hi>Iudas</hi> will ſell his maſter, and what not? Thirdly, they are moſt hard to part with: for if a ſeparation be endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be made but onely in point of affection; away with <hi>Amos,</hi> impriſon <hi>Michaiah,</hi> purſue <hi>Eliah,</hi> behead <hi>Iohn;</hi> they dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, ſnarle at the chaine that reſtraines them, and like ſome laſcivious novice, <note n="b" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>will not endure ſound words.</hi> But if once it comes to an actuall ſeparation, they are as deare, and they will as eaſily part with their <note n="c" place="margin">Chaldaei appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant nummum <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> sangui nem.</note> blood as them: the breaking of a deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, the budding of diſgrace, (as in <hi>Hamans</hi>) you may read in their face, you neede not aske what ayles them; nay many times their burden is ſo great, as they apprehend, that (to uſe <hi>Iobs</hi> phraſe) it makes ſome <note n="d" place="margin">Job 7.15.</note> 
               <hi>chuſe ſtrangling rather then life.</hi> But no ſuch adoe for this high God; there is none ſayes, <note n="e" place="margin">Job 35.10.</note> 
               <hi>Where is my maker?</hi> he may be where he will for them, ſo they have the world at will: and indeede, if at any time they looke up to him, tis not to honour, but make <note n="f" place="margin">Multi uti Deo volunt ut fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur mundo; Aug.</note> uſe of him for their owne carnall ends. In a time of dearth, or other miſery they will <note n="g" place="margin">Hoſea 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>howle upon their beds,</hi> not for their God, but for their <hi>corne, oyle and wine,</hi> for ſuch things as they ſtand in neede of, but care not, were it not for theſe things, what becomes of this great God, or <note n="h" place="margin">Eſay 43.24. Amos 2.13.</note> how much they ſinne againſt him. Secondly, is it any better in our feares? Indeed we talke much of fearing God, but where is the man that lifts up God on high in his heart, by making him <hi>his</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Eſay 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>dread?</hi> That acknowledges ſo his eminencie with reverence, as to ſtand in awe of him above all creatures? Alas, firſt, how heedeleſſe are we to provoke him, <note n="k" place="margin">Job 15.16.</note> 
               <hi>drinking in ſinne, as the fiſh doth water,</hi> without any dread at all, <note n="l" place="margin">Prov. 10.23.</note> 
               <hi>making a ſport of ſin,</hi> whereas true <note n="m" place="margin">Prov. 13.13. Ezra 10 3.</note> feare would make us reverence his
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156167:9"/> Commandements to doe them, it would make us to <note n="n" place="margin">Prov. 8.13.</note> hate ſin, and abſtaine from it, where <note n="o" place="margin">Gen. 42.18.</note> no eye ſees; and give up our ſelves to doe what he enjoynes with <note n="p" place="margin">2 Chron. 19.9.</note> ſtrife and conſtancie. Secondly, how regardleſſe of making up our breaches? we can eate and ſleepe, and be merry, when our provocations lye upon us; like <note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 24 38.</note> 
               <hi>Ioſephs</hi> brethren, or the <note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 37.25. Pſal. 119.</note> old world, and never heede them. Thirdly, how incredulous and ſleighting of his judgements? whereas, if we feared him, we would feare his blowes: either becauſe we <note n="s" place="margin">Pſal. 10.4, 5.</note> ſee them not; or Gods <note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 2.4.</note> patience ſuſpends the exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of them, to draw us to repentance, we ſay they ſhall not come. Though they hang in the threatning which cannot lye, we ſay, <note n="u" place="margin">Jer. 15.3.</note> 
               <hi>the words of the Prophet ſhall become as wind.</hi> Though they be evident in the cauſes procuring, as vapours aſcending, clouds gathering, yet we ſay they ſhall not be. Though they be manifeſt in the <note n="w" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.</note> parallels of our condition, which are left up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on record in Gods booke, and evident elſewhere, yet we dread them not; as if either he that cannot lye, had miſtaken; or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice it ſelfe for our ſakes, and in our particulars would become partiall; or omnipotencie could be withſtood, or ſtood under in executing wrath by our weakeneſſe. Tis a ſad caſe my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, that nothing but blowes will make us feare; when God falls a plaguing, then uſually men a fearing. The <hi>Aegyptians</hi> were gallant enough till Gods blowes made them ſtoope, and the <hi>Philistims</hi> high more then enough, when the victory fell on their ſide, and the Arke to boote, they thought they had met with another Dagon, ſuch a god as their owne, with whom they might be bold; but when he puts forth his power, as a man that wakes out of ſleepe, and ſmites his enemies (as the <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 78.653 66.</note> Pſalmiſt ſpeakes) in the hinder parts with Emrods, then they feare. But O how deplorable a thing is it, that even this feare uſually laſts not long; when plague, ſword, famine, or the like judgements, come firſt amongſt us! They are like the blocke that <hi>Iupiter</hi> in the <note n="y" place="margin">Euripid.</note> fable threw downe amongſt the croaking frogs, which at firſt was ſo terrible, that happie was he that could ſooneſt flye and get fartheſt off into the ſecretſt hole; but when they were a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better acquainted with it, they put away their dread, and now being feareleſſe, hopt, and leapt upon it: ſo as the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment continues, our feare growes leſſe, as if either God had ſtir'd up all his wrath, and ſo in time it would come to nothing: or
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156167:10"/> becauſe others were ſwept away by the <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 28.15.</note> 
               <hi>overflowing ſcourge</hi> and we reſpited, that therefore for the future it ſhall not <hi>come nigh us.</hi> So that by what hath beene ſpoken 'tis ſufficiently plain, that both in our <hi>love,</hi> and <hi>feare,</hi> we have brought this high God ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding low.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 12.34.</note> Out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeakes: O how in many places of this Land are mens glory (<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 57.8.</note> So the Pſalmiſt ſtiles our tongues) become their ſhame! ſpeaking of his glorious and reverent name, at which Angels are full of holy tremblings, with ſuch lightneſſe, and vanity; not lifting it up as their badge, glory, banner, as the <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod. 20.8.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> quod ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nif. elevavit tanquam vexil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum.</note> third Commandement injoynes. Nay with ſuch impiety and prophaneneſſe toſſing it to and fro, as if their ſpeech could have no grace, but in Gods diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, nor they honour, but in his diſhonour; as if <hi>Augustus Caeſar</hi> were a dealing with ſome god <hi>Neptune,</hi> or the <note n="e" place="margin">Lonic. Thect. Hiſtor.</note> three ſonnes trying their archery at their fathers heart, to ſee who can ſhoote nigheſt. Remember God will not hold ſuch guiltleſſe, he hath profeſt it: <note n="f" place="margin">Zach. 5.3.</note> there is a roule of curſes gone out to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Gods vengeance on ſuch. And if the pettieſt Prince will not endure to have his name abuſed and ſleighted; neer thinke the higheſt will permit it: no, he hath threatned that for it the <note n="g" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.2, 3.</note> Land ſhall mourne, and the inhabitants beſhrew the time that ere they did ſo. And thus you ſee the indignities we have put upon him, and how low we have brought him in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, have we not uſed him, as ill in his Ordinances; Ah alas! here we have brought him exceeding low indeede: though his Word, and Sacraments be, <note n="h" place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18.</note> Glaſſes manifeſting his goodneſſe and glory, Thrones of his Majeſtie, <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 119.9. James 1.18.</note> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels of grace, the ſoules <note n="k" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19</note> light, <note n="l" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2.</note> food, <note n="m" place="margin">Jer. 8.22.</note> phyſicke, <note n="n" place="margin">Eſay 12.3.</note> wells of Salvation; Yet how have we <note n="o" place="margin">Ezek. 22.8.</note> 
               <hi>deſpiſed Gods holy things?</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Hoſ. 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>the great things of his ſeeme to us but ſmall.</hi> Our fathers would have beene glad to have had their eyes bleſt with ſeeing what we have ſeene, and eares, with hearing what we have heard: But alas, with thoſe in <note n="q" place="margin">Mal. 1.13.</note> 
               <hi>Malachi, What a wearineſſe is it to us?</hi> we are quickly out of breath, ſoone tyred with duty, Gods Word is <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer. 23.33.34</hi> Quanto melius eſſet nonnullis omnino non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire verbum Dei, quam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire cum mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia, vel aud<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re cum hypocriſi, &amp;c. Hilar in Pſal. <hi>118.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>a burden to us.</hi> There are too many amongſt us that thinke, there is no ſuch great need of theſe, they can doe as well without them. And ô how ſad a ſight is it to any Godly
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156167:10"/> mind to ſee, with how much irreverence, and diſreſpect we uſe Gods Ordinances, <note n="s" place="margin">Levit. 26 2. Eccleſ 5.1. Pſal. 95.6.</note> though he command the contrary! were it but the letter, or token of ſome great Prince, our reverence, and reſpect would far exceede, what we ſhew to theſe. This is a too too common, but moſt grievous fault. Nay, how have ſome indeavoured to ſuppreſſe them if not in being, <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Eurip.</note> yet in reſpect of puritie, and power: as if, ſo we had the things, and did the outſide of the worke for faſhions ſake, 'twere no great matter after what ſort we did it; or whether we were advantaged by it or no.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We have uſed him as ill,<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 39.2, 3.</note> brought him as low in his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. 1. In his common traine; his Saints, though they be his, <note n="u" place="margin">Coloſ. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>Image,</hi> 
               <note n="w" place="margin">Exod. 19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>chiefe treaſure,</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>Iewels, favourites</hi> of heavens, <note n="x" place="margin">Mal. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings</hi> to the place where they be, <note n="z" place="margin">Gen. 19.22.</note> 
               <hi>pillars</hi> to keep off ill, <hi>prevailing Iacobs to precure good,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Zach. 2.7.</note> deare to God as the <hi>apple of his eye,</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Act 9.4. Mat. 25.40.45.</note> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 4 13.</note> ſuch whoſe grace or diſgrace he ownes as done to himſelfe, yet how have they beene <note n="c" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.3.</note> deſpiſed, and ſleighted in their thoughts by this generation, accounted as the off-ſcowring of the earth, the fooles of the age? The better Saint the worſe eſteeme; they have beene accounted as <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 31.22.</note> 
               <hi>broken veſſels,</hi> good for nothing but the dunghill; <note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 8.18.</note> 
               <hi>ſignes</hi> and <hi>wonders</hi> in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> the <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 69.12.</note> 
               <hi>Song of drunkards; the</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 35.15.16.</note> 
               <hi>mirth of feaſts:</hi> What names have beene invented to brand and diſgrace them with? what ſlanders and calumnies have not beene raiſed on them? that they are the <note n="i" place="margin">Act. 24.5. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>peſts</hi> of kingdomes; <note n="k" place="margin">1 King. 18.17.</note> 
               <hi>troublers of Iſrael;</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth. 38.</hi> Chriſtiam ad ignem; Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani ad lcones, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Rebellious</hi> againſt all lawes; not for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of the Common wealth, that they ſhould be permitted to draw in the common breath? how <note n="m" place="margin">Jer. 20.10.</note> 
               <hi>watching for their haltings; how</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 35.15, 25, 16.</note> 
               <hi>glad of their falls?</hi> How joyfull of catching at, and take up any ill rumor of them? how inſulting over their weakeneſſes? how wittie to revive the <note n="p" place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccleſ. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> old Primitive ſlaunders? and in a word, how cruell and mercileſſe to them,<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 41.8.</note> if they fall under their power? The <note n="q" place="margin">Plin. hiſt. nat.</note> Naturaliſt ſayes, the Tigers rage is ſtirr'd up, and exaſperated by ſmelling the fragrant ſent of ſpices: I am ſure 'tis thus with them, for doubtleſſe, becauſe <note n="r" place="margin">Eſay 59.15.</note> 
               <hi>they abstaine from evill</hi> (there is the cauſe) <hi>they make themſelves a prey;</hi> 
               <note n="s" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>they runne not with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot, but</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">Wiſd. 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>their wayes are of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother faſhion: there is cauſe enough; they ſhine as lights</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Phil. 2.15. Fonus homi, ſod Chriſtianus, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>in the midſt of a froward and perverſe generation,</hi> there is the true ground of the quarrell, what ere they pretend to the contrary. Well here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156167:11"/> the Saints have their <note n="w" place="margin">Pſal. 123.3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>hearts,</hi> as well as their hands full: out of the bitterneſſe of their ſoules they cry; Let me tell you in our Saviours phraſe, <note n="x" place="margin">Luk. 18.7.8.</note> 
               <hi>God will avenge his Saints and that ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily.</hi> If their prayers aſcend, and cryes enter into the eares of the Lord of Hoſts; the earth ſhall know their folly, and the next newes we heare is, <note n="y" place="margin">Revel. 8.4. &amp;c.</note> thunders, lightnings, earthquakes, and terrible judgements upon the world, to teſtifie Gods indignation for his peoples unworthy uſage.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In his more ſpeciall ſervants, his Miniſters. Are not they <note n="z" place="margin">Jer. 15.19.</note> Gods mouth? <note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> to his people? are not they the <note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Pen,</hi> and the <hi>holy Ghoſt the Inke,</hi> wherewith the grace and mind of the ever glorious God is written, on the fleſhly tables of his peoples hearts? Doth he not ſo farre owne them, as to ſay, <note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>He that heares you, heares me, &amp;c.</hi> Yet how in divers places of this Kingdome, have many of theſe beene ſleighted, ſnib'd, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, threatned, rob'd of their livelihood, their mouthes ſtopt, and al manner of indignities &amp; affronts offered to them; and what's the cauſe? Alas, if they would but have <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 30.10.</note> modified, and brought downe their light to the allay of the times, that their words might have beene as the <note n="e" place="margin">1 King. 22.13.</note> reſt of the Prophets: <note n="f" place="margin">Amos 7.12.13.</note> if they would but have quencht their zeale, abated of their diligence, and widened their conſcience in a way of blind obedience, to have ſwallowed Camels, they might have done well enough. But if Chriſt himſelfe ſit <note n="g" place="margin">Mal. 3 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>as the refiners fire, and fullers ſoape to purifie, and cleanſe the ſons of Levie, they will never endure his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming.</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Strabo l. <hi>17.</hi> Sic in fabula Ranae Solis nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptias execran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, Aeſop. fab. <hi>Revel.</hi> 16.8, 9, 10.</note> There are a people I have read of, that curſe the ſunne when it riſes; but 'tis becauſe it ſcorches them: <note n="i" place="margin">Joh. 5.53. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> is too <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſhining a light,</hi> to be long endured; and was it not plaine dealing brought that glorious Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> to be ſawne in peeces? <note n="k" place="margin">Hieron. in Eſai c. <hi>1.</hi> ex Rabin's.</note> Saint <hi>Ierom</hi> tells us, it was firſt becauſe he ſaid he had ſeene the Lord; and ſecondly, becauſe he call'd the great ones of <hi>Iudah</hi> 
               <note n="m" place="margin">Eſay 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>Princes of Sodome, and rulers of Gomorrah,</hi> who were indeede their trueſt paralells. Tis a ſad thing my brethren, and worth our laying to heart this day, to call to minde, what nets have beene ſpread,<note n="l" place="margin">Eſay 6.1.</note> what ſnares layd, what traps ſet, what ſuperfluous, if not ſuperſtitious ceremonies revived for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of faithfull painfull Miniſters;<note n="n" place="margin">Hoſ. 5.1.</note> whereas, give me leave to tell you my thoughts freely, I conceive 'twere better that <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſhould breake all <note n="o" place="margin">Sueton. in Auguſt.</note> 
               <hi>Vedius Pollioes</hi> curious glaſſes, then
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156167:11"/> that they ſhould break the bond of charity, or the breach of them be the occaſion of ſo much inhumanity as heretofore.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To name no more particulars; we have brought God as low in his Day, as in any of the former: though it be a Day of commemoration of one of the greateſt mercies; <note n="p" place="margin">Nundinae animae.</note> a Day of ſpeciall communion with God in his Ordinances; <note n="q" place="margin">Ezek. 20 20.</note> a ſigne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and his people; a type of our eternall reſt in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; a Day of Gods owne inſtitution; yet how in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this kingdome hath it beene prophaned? We have beene ſo farre from calling it <hi>Honourable,</hi> that we have made it <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary;</hi> a Day <note n="r" place="margin">Sabbatum vituli aurci. <hi>Exod. 32.6.</hi>
               </note> of ſports, paſtimes and recreations; we have <note n="ſ" place="margin">Eſay 58.13.</note> 
               <hi>done our owne works,</hi> and <hi>ſpoke our owne words;</hi> Nay, alas! in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places, there is no day in the weeke, wherein the devill hath beene more ſerved in revellings, drunkenneſſe, and all manner of ungodlineſſe, then on that Day. We have beene ſo far from eſteeming it a delight, that no day hath beene a greater burden to us, accounting the worke of that day moſt irkeſome, and the <note n="t" place="margin">Amos 8.5.</note> time moſt tedious.</p>
            <p>And thus you ſee a ſad ſight, how both in Himſelfe, his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Servants, Day, we have offered indignity to the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and brought him low amongſt us in this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>O, how hath God thundered againſt theſe abaſings of him in his word! <note n="u" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> Do we deſpiſe him? there is contempt for us; Do we ſleight his Ordinances? <note n="w" place="margin">Levit. 26.15.26.</note> there is diſeaſes to conſume us; Do we trample upon his Saints? <note n="x" place="margin">Luke 18.8.</note> there is deſtruction to overtake us; Doe we prophane his Sabbaths? <note n="y" place="margin">Levit. 26.34, 35.</note> there is deſolation to reward us; Nay, hath not God executed his fierce diſpleaſure for theſe indignities upon tranſgreſſing Nations? What brought ruine on Iſraels Kingdome? <note n="z" place="margin">Ezek. 22.24. &amp;c.</note> were not theſe the cauſe? What deſolation on Judah? <note n="a" place="margin">Zach. 7.13. &amp;c. 2 Chron. 36.15, 16.</note> were not theſe the ſins? We need not goe to Shiloh; alas, nigher hand we may behold, in Germany, Ireland, ſad ſpectacles of Gods revenging Juſtice. Nay, even at home, how faſt doe the clouds gather threatning tempeſt? Our heaven is darkned, our Sun and Moone withhold their light, our Stars have loſt their luſter, our Land trembles, the foundations ſhake; and may we not feare that theſe iniquities in us make our condition like ſinfull Judahs; as a <note n="b" place="margin">Eſay 30.13, 14.</note> 
               <hi>breach in a high wall</hi> (as the Prophet elegantly expreſſeth it) <hi>whoſe ruine cometh in an inſtant when leaſt expected?</hi> Or (as it followes) as the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156167:12"/> 
               <hi>breaking of a Potters veſſell</hi> all to pieces without hope of repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? What ſhall we doe? Shall we cry the <note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 7.4.</note> Temple of the Lord? <note n="d" place="margin">Dum ſancte vivimus Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſumus, &amp;c. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
               </note> that will not ſerve; or plead <note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> 
               <hi>we are Abrahams ſeed?</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">Non quaeritur ſucceſſio carnis, ſed fidei haerc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditas. <hi>Aug.</hi>
               </note> it will not excuſe: If we were <note n="g" place="margin">Ier. 22.24.</note> 
               <hi>Coniahs,</hi> as the ſignet on Gods right hand, theſe things would pluck us thence. Shall we carowſe away our feares like <note n="h" place="margin">Dan. 5.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> verſe 30. <hi>Tranquillitas illa tempeſtas eſt,</hi> Bern.</note> 
               <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> beſieged by the Medes and Perſians? Or like the Cyclops, immure our ſelves in our caves of carnall confidence without all dread? Or like the Thracians when it thunders, ſhoot up our arrowes of defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt the Higheſt? Alas, hereby wee may make our ruine more ſwift, more certaine, but not evade it. If now the <note n="i" place="margin">Hoſ. 7.9.</note> ſymptomes of our miſery begin to ſhew themſelves, we would not palliat, but throughly cure Englands malady; wee muſt take away the cauſe, and the effect will follow: firſt quit our ſelves of theſe indignities we have offered God, <note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 18.7, 8.</note> and then we may aſſure our ſelves the quarrell is ended. And that wee may do ſo; give me leave to ſhew you, 1. Firſt their <hi>riſe,</hi> the <hi>roots of bitterneſſe</hi> from whence they ſpring. 2. And then their <hi>Remedy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As I conceive, theſe are the roots of bitterneſſe, from whence debaſing of God in this kingdome ariſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The lewd lives and wicked actions of ſome that profeſſe Religion, &amp; pretend relation to the Higheſt. <note n="l" place="margin">De fide cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que magis ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis quam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus creden li. <hi>Ruffin.</hi>
               </note> They have <hi>Iacobs</hi> voice, but <hi>Eſaus</hi> hands; either they are <note n="m" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.10.12.</note> 
               <hi>idle buſie-bodies,</hi> not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king at all, but only prating of Religion; or if they do work, they are <note n="n" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13.15.</note> full of deceit, and all manner of injuſtice in their dealings, like the Harpies, Virgins faces, but Vultures tallons: for, looke into their trading; what <note n="o" place="margin">Mic. 6.11.</note> unfaithfulneſſe, over-reaching, couſenage? weigh their words; <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ier. 9.3.</hi> Crimina qui cernunt aliorum nec ſ<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>a cernunt; Hi ſapu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aliis, deſipiunt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſibi. <hi>Owen Ep. Mat. 7.5.</hi>
               </note> what lying, ſlaundering, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting, cenſoriouſneſſe? Looke into their actions; what griping, oppreſſion, cruelty ſhall you finde? Alas, theſe are ſo farre from <note n="q" place="margin">Tit. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>gracing the doctrine</hi> of the Higheſt, or cauſing others by their example to <note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> 
               <hi>give him glory,</hi> that by their carriage the mouths of ungodly men are opened wide to ſpeak evill of Religion, and <note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>blaſpheme Gods name.</hi> They are ſtumbling blocks in the way of others; but I wiſh they would take to heart thoſe dreadfull words of Chriſt, <note n="t" place="margin">Mar. 18.6, 7. <hi>Errorum cauſae ſunt.</hi> 1 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 Tim. 6.4. 2 <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2 Pet. 3.16. 3 <hi>Philoſophiae abuſus,</hi> Coloſ. 2.8. ut <hi>Aerius, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Offences muſt come, but woe to thoſe</hi> by whom they come; it were better a milſtone were tied about their necks, and they caſt into the bottome of the ſea, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Multitudes of errors that daily ſpring up amongſt us,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156167:12"/> Men dreame their Midianitiſh dreame, and tell it for Goſpel to their neighbours. O! how is our Kingdome peſtered with Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagianiſme, Socinianiſme, Arminianiſme, Anabaptiſme, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, Popery, Libertiniſme, and what Sect findes not abetters in our Land? How doe theſe ſpread like a <note n="u" place="margin">Tim. 2.7.</note> 
               <hi>gangren?</hi> and get ground every day? how do they like the Locuſts of Egypt corrupt and deſtroy our Spring, our hopefull youth before they come to maturity? Alas, how is the peace both of Church and Common-wealth, by theſe diſturbed, and the unity rent in pieces? How are families disjoynted, and the Kingdome divided within it ſelfe? what heats are ſtruck amongſt neereſt friends for theſe? what malice, heart-burnings, and ingagements againſt each other? ſo that wee may well revive that expreſſion uſed by <note n="w" place="margin">Nullae infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtae hominibus beſtie, ut ſunt ſibi ferales ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique Chriſtiani <hi>Ammian. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. lib. 2. ca. 2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus</hi> (a ſad thing that a Heathen ſhould ſee ſuch helliſh miſcarriages of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s towards each other) There are no beaſts to men (ſaith he) ſo cruell and deadly, as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are. Well; hereby there are many corrupted, and drawne away; and very many turne Scepticks, concluding nothing in matter of Religion, nor much regarding piety, truth, Saints, Sabbath, or ought elſe that is ſpirituall, debaſe God in all; for they conceive, that either in theſe there is no reality, or if there be, that it is far above their ability ere to reach it; and under theſe diſcouragements they ſit them downe, reſolving to give themſelves the raines in carnall liberty, and never to trouble their heads or hearts about ſuch inquiries, or the practice of things ſo controverted as theſe are.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Heapes of baſe and unworthy Miniſters, they bring God low; when they are ſuch, either in reſpect of,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Gifts and abilities. <note n="x" place="margin">Eſay 42.19.</note> Lanthornes without light, breaſts without milke, <note n="y" place="margin">Iude 12.</note> clouds without water, eyes without ſight, <note n="z" place="margin">Zach. 11.16, 17. Mat. 15.14.</note> guides without eyes; they are ſo far from the Apoſtles hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exclamation, <note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>Who is ſufficient for theſe things,</hi> that in their opinion, he that is good for nothing elſe, is able enough for this: If we have a child we know not what to doe with, O, make a Miniſter of him! When all trades faile, are there not too too many make this their laſt refuge? Thus, the <note n="b" place="margin">2 Chro. 13.9.</note> 
               <hi>baſeſt</hi> of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are thruſt on God, who (to uſe <hi>Rehoboams</hi> phraſe) <hi>are good enough to ſerve dunghill-gods, or thoſe that are no gods,</hi> but not the Higheſt. It is Gods cuſtome, firſt to gift, and then to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156167:13"/> as he <hi>Bezaleel;</hi> and as for the meaſure, we ſhall finde that God appointed, <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Aynſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth on Gen. c. 20. ver. 16. 1 King 7.15. compared with 2 Chron. 3.15. Allow for the baſis one cubit and it doubles the number.</note> both the weights, and meaſures of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary to be twice as large as thoſe of the Common-wealth; to ſhew, that he expects much more in thoſe that ſerve him there, then he doth in others.</p>
            <p>Secondly, baſe in judgement, and opinion. <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 3 12.</note> O my people, thy teachers have made thee to erre, and perverted the ſteps of thy way! A ſad complaint; the people cry for bread, and they give them a ſtone; for meat, and they reach them a Serpent; for drink, and there is none proceeds from theſe fountaines, <note n="e" place="margin">Rev. 8.9, 11.</note> but deadly ſtreames; for viſion, and they hold out to them <note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 23.16.</note> the thoughts of their owne hearts, dreames of theit owne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. They are farre from being what God requires they ſhould be; cleane Mirrors, to receive the beames of Gods truth into themſelves, and then by reflection to caſt forth <hi>thoſe</hi> beames upon the people: what they ſpeake, they ſhould receive <note n="g" place="margin">Ezek. 33.7.</note> 
               <hi>from Gods mouth,</hi> not the forge of Hereticks. It ought to bee their care, <note n="h" place="margin">Ier. 23.28.</note> to <hi>ſeparate betweene the precious and the vile;</hi> but this ſome cannot, others do not, and hence come ſuch creature ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing, but God-debaſing errors daily to ſpring amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, baſe in life and practice: Whereas they ought to be <note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.3.</note> 
               <hi>examples to their flocks,</hi> and to goe before believers by way of practiſe, in <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Tim. 4.12. Eſay 52.11.</hi> Quod ſumus profeſſione, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione potius quam nomine demonſtremus. Et nomen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruat actioni, actio reſpondeat nomini, ne ſit nomen inane &amp; cimen immane, &amp;c. <hi>Amb. l. De dignitate Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotali. c. 3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>converſation, charity, ſpirit, faith, purity,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeakes; they are ſo farre from this, that although per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, like high-way hands, they point out the way to others, yet walke not therein themſelves; juſt like the <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 23.3.</note> Phariſees, <hi>they ſay, i. e.</hi> they can teach others what to doe, but <hi>doe not, i. e.</hi> they practice not what they preach; <note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 2.21.</note> nay, <hi>they doe the things they forbid to others;</hi> They preach a man ſhould not ſteale, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit adultery, &amp;c. <note n="n" place="margin">Periit pietas à Sacerdot. &amp;c. <hi>Bern. in Cant. Hoſ. 4.9.</hi> Non arbitror inter Sacerdotes multos eſſe qui ſalvi ſiant, &amp;c. <hi>Chryſ. Hom. 3. in Act.</hi>
               </note> yet they do. By their example they infect more then their paines cure. God required in the Old Law <note n="o" place="margin">Levit. 21.22.</note> they ſhould be without blemiſh, by way of qualification; the ſame is required in the <note n="p" place="margin">1 Tim. 3.2.</note> New; for if they be like old <hi>Elies</hi> ſons in their lives and doings, <note n="q" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.12.</note> they will not only bring judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on their owne ſoules and bodies, but bring God low in the eyes, and make (as they did) his ſervice ſtink in the noſtrils of the people.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, or elſe they are baſe in paines, and diſcharge of their duty. <note n="r" place="margin">Eſay 56.11.</note> They will take the <hi>fleece,</hi> but the <hi>flock</hi> may fare as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:156167:13"/> it will for them; It may be (except to gather their in-come) they will ſcarce vouchſafe it a viſit: they little regard the <note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.1, 2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Apoſtolicall injunction of being inſtant, and <hi>preaching in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, out of ſeaſon;</hi> or the <note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.16.</note> woe threatned in caſe of non-perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance; <note n="u" place="margin">Eſay 56.19.</note> they love to ſlumber, ſleepe, lye downe, their carnall eaſe; the <note n="w" place="margin">Paſtorum abſentia lupo invadendi oca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem praebet. <hi>Athanaſ. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. Imperat.</hi>
               </note> wolfe may worry, the enemy <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 13.25.</note> ſow what tares he pleaſe in their field; Thus careleſſe are they of Gods diſhonour, and regardleſſe how low men bring him.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The remiſneſſe, and coldneſſe of many Magiſtrates in drawing the ſword of Juſtice againſt bringers of God low. They are not affected with Gods diſhonour as they ought to be; they can well enough indure (<note n="y" place="margin">Levit. 24.11. &amp;c. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>perforare.</hi>
               </note> contrary to <hi>Moſes</hi> preſident) to heare Gods name ſtruck through, torne in pieces, and trampled on by bloody oathes; his day prophaned, his Ordinances neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, or ſleightly uſed; his people wronged, and abuſed; yet here <note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 115.5.</note> like <hi>Davids</hi> Idol, they have eyes, and ſee not, eares, and heare not, &amp;c. but if by complaint made to them, they are forced to heare, they think as ſleightly, and accordingly proceed, as ſometimes <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 25.19.</note> 
               <hi>Feſtus</hi> did of <hi>Paul,</hi> and his cauſe, as if theſe things were not worth their heeding; which ſleighting and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardleſneſſe of theirs, ſtrengthens the hands of God-debaſing people in their prophaneneſſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The ill example and diſcountenance of Superiours. If the great ones be chiefe in the fault, <note n="b" place="margin">Ezra 9.2.</note> in <hi>Ezraes</hi> time, it is no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile if the people be infected with it; <note n="c" place="margin">Aethiopes eorum Principil inſirmitates imitant, &amp;c. <hi>Diod. Sicul.</hi>
               </note> we ſee a man of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty can no ſooner take up a faſhion in habit, but thouſands fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him; the truth is, there is nothing hath greater influence upon the multitude, nor ſwayes more with them, then the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of their betters; <note n="d" place="margin">2 Chro. 12.1. 2 Chron. 36.12.14.</note> if they contemne and ſleight all piety, the people will do ſo too.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The croſſes and meanneſſe (for the moſt part) of Gods people. <note n="e" place="margin">Zeph 3.12.</note> A poore people, and afflicted, that is their character. <note n="f" place="margin">Euſch. hiſt. Eccleſ. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> Chriſts kinſmen were not more contemptible to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Domitian,</hi> for their meane condition, then theſe to the <note n="g" place="margin">Ioh. 7.48.</note> great and wiſe ones of the world; and for their ſakes, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The <note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 3.2.</note> cowardiſe and faint-heartedneſſe of thoſe that are religious. If they come into the company of godleſſe men, they diſſemble what they are, for feare of <note n="i" place="margin">Iohn 7.13.</note> diſpleaſing men, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156167:14"/> affronted by them, <note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 9.3.</note> they are not valiant for their God; their tongue is tied, their light of a godly converſation is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained; their carnall policy makes them forget <note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 5.16.</note> Chriſts precept.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The vayling of providence. When God ſeemes to <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 44.23.</note> ſleep; <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 10.1.</note> hide himſelfe; <note n="o" place="margin">Ezek. 8.12.</note> forſake the earth, by the ſuſpenſion of the manifeſt working of his power; then (becauſe the world lives in ſenſe, and not in faith) God is exceeding low both in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and all that pertaines to him in their eſteeme; they ſay with that <note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 14 1.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſtultus à radice <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> efſlornit.</note> ſapleſſe fellow in their hearts, <hi>There is no God;</hi> or with proud <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Exod. 5.2.</note> 
               <hi>Who is the Lord?</hi> If they grant there is one <note n="r" place="margin">Non vacat exiguis rebus adeſſe Jovi. <hi>Iob 22.14.</hi>
               </note>, they confine him to the heavens; or if they will allow him the earth for a part of his territories, they fancy him ſuch a God as will <note n="ſ" place="margin">Zeph. 1.12.</note> 
               <hi>neither do good nor evill.</hi> Now on the contrary, <note n="t" place="margin">Ezek. 38.23. Pſal. 9.16.</note> when God puts forth his power in working any great unexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted change in the world, the notion of God that nature hath planted in mens minds revives, and God recovers his glory. <note n="u" place="margin">Ezek. 36.23.</note> When he puls downe Babylon, whereas Gods name was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned before in the eyes of the Heathen, <hi>i. e.</hi> they thought as meanly of the true God, nay more meanly then of ſome of their owne dead ſtocks they worſhiped; they tooke him for a very common, ordinary God: But by this manifeſtation of his might, and diſcovery of his Juſtice, in the ruine of a place ſo ſtrong, ſo oppoſite to himſelfe, and ſervice, his name is now ſanctified in the ſight of the Heathen, <hi>i. e.</hi> lifted up above all their Idol-gods, and he is taken notice of to be <hi>the Lord.</hi> So likewiſe, when he raiſes Sion out of her deſolate condition, <note n="w" place="margin">Pſal. 102.16.</note> 
               <hi>He then appeares ſo in his glory,</hi> that the Saints admire, and <note n="x" place="margin">Pſ. 126.2, 3.</note> the very Heathens themſelves are aſtoniſhed at it; but <note n="y" place="margin">Pſ. 74 11.</note> when Sion fals by the enemies hand, then the fooliſh people blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme and deſpiſe Gods name.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, (which indeed is the roote of all, and without which all the reſt were nothing) a dark ſenſuall heart, either 1. <note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.14.</note> not diſcerning the things of God, <hi>The naturall man doth not, neither can he, for they are ſpiritually diſcerned;</hi> They may have indeed a <note n="a" place="margin">Cognitio <hi>1.</hi> Diſciplinaris. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>diſciplinary</hi> knowledge, <hi>i. e.</hi> a knowledge by heareſay, as a blind man hath of colours; but an <note n="b" place="margin">Intuitiva <hi>i. e.</hi> per ſpeciem propriam, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>intuitive</hi> knowledge, that he wants; hee ſees neither the glory of the Higheſt, nor the ſweetneſſe of Ordinances, the benefit of his Day, or the beauty
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156167:14"/> of holineſſe in his ſervants; he looks upon <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 26.7.14.</note> the outſide of the Tabernacle, and there are onely meane deſpicable coverings; but as for the coſtly furniture, and admirable beauty within, that he ſees not, much leſſe hath he the leaſt apprehenſion of the glory of God that dwels in the Holy of Holies betweene the Cherubims. It is no marvaile therefore, though the carnall mind ſo much deſpiſe that, which to it ſelfe appeares <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 5. 1 Cor. 2.6, 7, 8. 1 Iohn 3.2. Coloſ. 3.3.</note> ſo contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and of whoſe hidden glory it knows juſt nothing at all.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Nor can it more reliſh the Higheſt, or the things of God: there is no proportion betwixt a carnall heart and them, they are contrary to its humour and temper, wayes and courſes, thoughts and projects, ends and aimes; <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 8.7.</note> therefore the Apoſtle ſayes, the carnall mind is enmity againſt God, it is not, neither can it be ſubject to the Law of God; It ſleights his Day, and contemnes his Ordinances, deſpiſes his Saints, and rejects him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as unprofitable, uſeleſſe and diſadvantagious to it ſelfe. And thus you ſee the roots from whence this debaſing of God amongſt us comes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But now perhaps you will ſay to me, The diſeaſe is plaine enough, and the cauſes manifeſt, but where is the cure? O what may wee doe in theſe times of publique miſery to helpe all?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Doubtleſſe my beloved, if you would ſtanch the bloody iſſue that already afflicts the Kingdome; if you would ſettle the peace of Church and State; if you deſire the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of your ſelves and yours, here is the way, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Let God be uſed like himſelfe, ſet up on high in our eſteeme and actions.</p>
            <p>Let us firſt repaire God in point of honour, againſt
<list>
                  <item>1. Our ſelves.</item>
                  <item>2. Others.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, againſt our ſelves; alas, there is not any of us, but leſſe or more, by one meanes or other, wee have had our hands in bringing him low; therefore I beſeech you, let us not be like the <hi>Lamiae,</hi> cleare ſighted abroad, but without eyes at home; rather looke into our owne hearts and wayes, where we ſhall ſee there is cauſe enough why we ſhould uſe our utmoſt indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to free our ſelves from the guilt of the frequent, and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid indignities we have put upon him, and to repaire him in point of honour.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:156167:15"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But you will aske me, What are the meanes whereby we may repaire his glory in reſpect of our ſelves?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Let us take to our ſelves our owne ſhame, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge our God-diſhonouring courſes, and in the ſenſe of them lie low before him; For is not this the buſineſſe of the day, to feed our ſoules with the ſad ſpectacle of our ill carriages towards our God, and thereby to make our heart to bow? If we put off our ornaments, and not our pride; if the head hang downe, and the heart be lifted up, are we in better ſtate, or can we expect better ſucceſſe of our faſt, then the Prophet <note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 58.</note> 
               <hi>Eſayes</hi> hypocrites found by theirs? But, if we ſeriouſly in the ſenſe of our owne vildneſſe humble our ſelves this day before our God, <note n="g" place="margin">Ier. 3.12, 13.</note> Do our ſins trouble us? he will diſcharge them; <note n="h" place="margin">2 Chro. 7.14.</note> Is he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted? this will cauſe him to returne, and heale our Land. Would we gaine audience this day? the <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 9.12.</hi> Et cum talis fueris memento mei. <hi>Bern.</hi>
               </note> prayer of the humble ſelf-abhorring ſoule cannot miſcarry: or would we get a glimpſe of the Higheſt? he that would ſee ſtars in the day, muſt deſcend into ſome pit, from thence he may diſcerne them: See <note n="k" place="margin">Pro. 30.2, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon,</hi> when he fals loweſt in the ſenſe of his own vild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, he riſes then higheſt in the apprehenſion of Gods glory. Would we have Gods directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in theſe diſtracting erring times, what to do in our private Chriſtian practiſe? He <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 25.9.</note> will teach the humble his wayes, <note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 138.6.</note> he gives grace to them, but beholds the proud afar off: or what courſe to ſteere in Church or State, according to our ſeverall places? If we would but put on this temper and frame of ſpirit, <note n="n" place="margin">Ezek. 43.11.</note> we ſhall not want that neither.</p>
            <p>Seeing therefore, this ſelf-humbling, ſelf-debaſing, is both the work of the day, and a thing ſo requiſite; give me leave to further you in it; and to the ſame end, to lay before you cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain conſiderations, wherein we may all of us ſee enough to make us vilde in our own eyes. Conſider we therefore:</p>
            <p n="1">1. What <note n="o" place="margin">Ier. 8 6. 1 King. 8.47.</note> have we done? How many Sabbaths have we prophaned? How many opportunities of exalting God have we let ſlip? How many Sermons have we ſleighted? How many Lords Suppers by unpreparedneſſe and irreverence polluted? How in our love and feare, hath every vanity been ſet up, and God debaſed? How low, and ſeldome is God in our thoughts? How little is God extold by our tongues? How farre are our actions from advancing his name in the world? There is no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156167:15"/> number can count our rebellions, or reckon up our diſthroniza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Higheſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What are we that have done theſe things? for <note n="p" place="margin">Gen. 18.27.</note> matter, duſt and aſhes; for weakeneſſe, <note n="q" place="margin">Eſay 40.6, 17</note> graſſe, eaſily withering, flowers, quickly fading; for emptineſſe, vanity, lighter then vanity, nothing, nay leſſe then nothing; <note n="r" place="margin">Ezek. 15.2. &amp;c.</note> like <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, good for nothing: A ſweet contemptible ſubject, to lift up our ſelves againſt this God of glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Againſt whom have we exalted our ſelves? Is it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Higheſt? A treſpaſſe againſt an ordinary man, being committed againſt the King, proves treaſon. Do not our hearts tremble? Were it againſt a King, it were too much, <note n="ſ" place="margin">Prov. 16.14.</note> 
               <hi>His wrath is as the meſſenger of death;</hi> But what is it then againſt the Kings King? againſt that God that infinitely ſurpaſſes all Princes of the earth in glory?</p>
            <p n="1">1. Were it againſt a man, <note n="t" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>the Iudge might judge our cauſe,</hi> but being againſt this high God, <hi>O! who ſhall intreat for us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. What recompenſation can we make for theſe indignities we have offered him? It is <note n="u" place="margin">Mic. 6.6.7.</note> not thouſands of Rams, not ten thouſands of rivers of Oyle, that he regards; to give the fruit of our body, for the ſin of our ſoule, he reſpects not. If we ſhould weepe out our eyes, grieve our ſelves into our grave, give our bodies to the fire; alas, it is an infinite Glory by our ſins we have wronged, and how can the finite ſufferings of ſuch worthleſſe creatures make amends for the injury, and diſhonour that we have done him? And this is one reaſon of the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingneſſe <note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. 5.26.</hi> Propter ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factionis defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, &amp;c.</note> of hels torments on the damned, becauſe being worthleſſe they cannot ſatisfie Gods juſtice in any time, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they undergoe his wrath for their demerits to all eternity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Where may we hide us from his purſuit, and vengeance? <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 139.8.</note> 
               <hi>Darkneſſe cannot cover us;</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Amos 9.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Carmel, nor the bottome of the ſea conceale us;</hi> going up <hi>to Heaven, or downe to hell</hi> ſecure us; all places are alike to him, for he is the place of places, they ſubſiſt in him; <note n="z" place="margin">Ier. 23.24.</note> 
               <hi>He fils them all,</hi> therefore to hide us is impoſſible.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By what power can we defend our ſelves againſt his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venging juſtice? How eaſily are <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 27.4. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 5.24. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 9.18, 19, 20.</note> thornes, and ſtubble ore-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by the fire? <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 1.4.</note> chaffe whift away by the winde? If wee were as well intrencht as <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> in Babylon; or fortified <note n="c" place="margin">Cedren.</note> as <hi>Nicephorus Phocas</hi> the Greek Emperour, who out of his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:156167:16"/> guilty conſcience fearing heavens juſtice made his Palace at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> as it was thought impregnable; whereby, he now ſecured, caſt off his feares; But when he leaſt expected, a voyce was heard, none knew from whom, or whence, taxing his foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh confidence, and telling him, that though he raiſed the walls as high as heaven, yet as long as wickedneſſe dwelt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, there was no ſafety to be expected. 'Tis <note n="d" place="margin">Eſay 2.12. &amp;c. Zeph. 1.14. &amp;c. Eſay 43.13. Amos 2.14, 15, 16.</note> not the ſtrength of towers, walls, or any creature, is able to ſecure us againſt his conſuming indignation.</p>
            <p n="5">5. What excuſe can we make for our ſelves? ſhall we ſay we did not know ſuch things to be indignities to the Higheſt? 'Twil not excuſe, we have his word, and may know it if we will. Or is it an abaſement to our conceited excellencie to ſerve the Higheſt? Alas, the ſervice of the greateſt Emperour or nobleſt maſter, which men ſo ſeeke, what is it to this? the <note n="e" place="margin">Revel. 19.10.</note> Angels and excellenteſt <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 116.16.</note> Saints account this their glory. Or is it no thriving ſervice? <note n="g" place="margin">Mal. 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>None lights a fire or opens a doore for nought.</hi> The end he aymes at in his Commands, is the good of his ſervants, <hi>that</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Deut. 5.33.</note> 
               <hi>they may live, &amp;c.</hi> There is no ſervice ſo gainfull here as this; there is <note n="i" place="margin">Pſa. 119.165.</note> peace, <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 4.7.</note> joy, proſperitie, <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 3.8.</note> bleſſing, riches, honour, all that is good; and as for the future, no maſter makes ſuch provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for ſervants as God for his; <note n="m" place="margin">Joh. 12.26. Revel. 22.3.</note> immortality, heaven, life, glory, and that for ever; ſo that we are wholly left without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whither may we appeale from his tribunall? there is none higher then himſelf, he is the ſole Judge, that <note n="n" place="margin">James 4.12.</note> hath power of eternall life and death; he is both <note n="o" place="margin">Eſay 33.22.</note> Lawgiver, Judge, and King; there is no appeale.</p>
            <p n="7">7. How ſhall we be able to ſtand under his wrath? If this high God doe but lift up his voyce, <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 18.13. &amp;c.</note> abroad flye haileſtones and coales of fire; The ſea roares, the earth trembles, the whole creation is troubled; who is able <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 76.7.</note> to ſtand before his indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? We talke much of lightning, what a terrible creature it is; how powerfull in executing Gods Commands; what ſtrange things it will doe; conſume houſes, nay Cities; rend and teare mighty trees, maſſie buildings in peeces; kill the child in the mothers wombe, with many other ſtrange and aſtoniſhing ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: we cannot ſay how great the power of that one creature is; how much leſſe doe we know what is of his wrath; 'tis like
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156167:16"/> himſelfe, <note n="a" place="margin">Nah. 1.6.</note> high and glorious, ſharpe and piercing even to the ſoule, bereaving that of peace, joy, courage: alas, <hi>our hearts</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. 22.14.</note> 
               <hi>cannot be ſtrong</hi> when this poſſeſſes them; nor indure, when this like a fierce Lyon <note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 29.20.</note> 
               <hi>couches</hi> and lyes upon them. <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Homer.</note> All the creatures combined cannot <hi>reſiſt it,</hi> nor any meere created means <note n="e" place="margin">Jer. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>extinguiſh</hi> it: being powred out, it makes the <note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 24 17.18. &amp;c. Jer. 4.19. &amp;c.</note> earth a deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the nations paſt eſcaping; the high ones come to nothing; the mighty ſtrengthleſſe, heartleſſe. What ſhall we doe now conſidering all theſe things? ſhall we ſtill goe on in a way of debaſing God? Who did ever contend with him and proſper? I remember <note n="g" place="margin">Herod. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Herodotus</hi> tells us a ſtory of the <hi>Pſilli</hi> a fooliſh people, who being diſpleaſed with the South winde, for drying up their waters, would needes take up armes againſt it; but while they marcht on the ſands to meete their enemie, it blew ſo ſtrongly, that it raiſed ſuch a drift of ſand as overwhelmed them; whereby, in ſtead of a victory, they met with a grave, as the juſt reward of their folly. The like, if we ſteere this courſe, we may expect, as in the <note n="h" place="margin">Job 22.15. &amp;c.</note> old world, the <note n="i" place="margin">Exod. 14.27. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and many others plainely appeares. In briefe, if we would <hi>active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> doe him honour, and our ſelves good; there is no way but to flye to him; and no poſture more meete, and acceptable then this <note n="k" place="margin">2 Chron. 33.12.</note> 
               <hi>Self abhorrencie, and lying low before him.</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Prov. 30.2. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>I am more brutiſh then any man, and have not the underſtanding of a man in me, &amp;c.</hi> ſhould (as they were <hi>Agurs</hi>) be every one of our thoughts. The <note n="m" place="margin">Luk 15.21.</note> prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall, or <note n="n" place="margin">Luk 18.13.</note> Publicans confeſſion well fits our mouths: their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture may ſhew us what behaviour beſt becomes us: were it to put on <note n="o" place="margin">1 King 21.27.</note> ſack-cloath, ſit in aſhes, cover our heads with duſt, with <hi>Ahab</hi> to walke the pace of ſaddeſt, dejectedſt mourners, it is not low enough, it cannot be too low, the God we have deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is ſo high, whom could we but get a ſight of, it would lay us low indeede, as ſometimes <note n="p" place="margin">Job 42.56. c. 7.20.</note> 
               <hi>Iob,</hi> and <note n="q" place="margin">Eſay 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay;</hi> 
               <note n="r" place="margin">Phil. 3.</note> and drive us out of our ſelves to take Sanctuary in Chriſts merit. And thus you ſee the firſt meanes whereby we ſhould repaire God in point of glory, in reſpect of our ſelves, <hi>viz.</hi> by taking to our ſelves our ſhame, and ſo lying low before him.</p>
            <p n="2">2, We <note n="s" place="margin">Ezra 10.1.</note> ſhould be deepely affected with, and mourne for, the indignities have beene offered to him. <note n="t" place="margin">Schickard. in Bechin. Happer.</note> If the booke of the Law did but fall to the ground amongſt the Jewes, they call'd a faſt, and it was matter of mourning to them; but ô how hath
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:156167:17"/> Gods law not onely falne to the ground amongſt us by omiſſion of practice, but beene <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 2.3.119 126. Eſay 24.5.</note> trampled upon by oppoſition and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt. <note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Diodor. Sicul.</hi> l. 17.</note> When one of <hi>Darius</hi> King of <hi>Perſia's</hi> Eunuchs ſaw <hi>Alexander</hi> the great ſetting his feete upon a low table that had beene highly eſteemed by his maſter, he wept; being askt the reaſon by <hi>Alexander,</hi> he gave this, he mourn'd to ſee that thing which his maſter ſo highly once eſteemed, to be now contemn'd and made his footeſtoole: ſo in truth my beloved, what pious heart doth not bleed to heare, and ſee in theſe degenerate times, the deſpiſing, and trampling upon thoſe things which God ſo highly prizes? His name is in every corner torne in pieces by bloody oathes, as if men were reſolved, if they could, to ſweare, and curſe God out of Heaven. What irreverence is uſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Ordinances? what contempt, and reproach caſt upon his ſervants? what a low opinion of God, of the power and purity of Religion, is there in the hearts of people? Theſe, and many ſuch like miſcarriages, may well make <note n="x" place="margin">Pſ. 119.136.</note> 
               <hi>our eyes runne downe with rivers of teares, becauſe,</hi> neither by our ſelves, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the high God is no more advanced, but ſo much debaſed amongſt us. To ſee earthly greatneſſe deſcend in ſtate, or eſteeme, hath ſometimes moved ingenuous minds to expreſſe their ſenſe by teares; <note n="y" place="margin">Sabel. l. <hi>6.</hi> Enn <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> for <hi>Darius</hi> treacherouſly murthered; <note n="z" place="margin">Diod. Sicul. l. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> the people, for <hi>Perſes</hi> King of Macedonia, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he were their enemy, yet ſeeing him brought from a Palace, to a priſon, wept. <note n="a" place="margin">1. Sam. 15.35</note> So <hi>Samuel</hi> for <hi>Saul,</hi> when he had loſt his eſteeme with God, and ſtability in his Kingdome, both together. But, if they that be brought low have any relation to us, we are much more moved: So <note n="b" place="margin">Sabellic. l. <hi>7.</hi> Enn. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pſammenitus</hi> King of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, ſeeing his familiar friend brought downe from a high to a very meane condition, teſtified his ſorrow by weeping. <note n="c" place="margin">Iob 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>Jobs</hi> friends did the like when they came to viſit him. And if our hands be in it, we are uſually much more ſenſible, and affected with it: <note n="d" place="margin">Eraſm. in Adag.</note> So <hi>Baſſianus,</hi> when ever he ſaw but the picture of his brother <hi>Geta,</hi> whom he had bereaved both of Crowne and life together. But, if our owne condition be engaged and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in theirs, then moſt of all. <note n="e" place="margin">2 Chron. 35.24.</note> Thus <hi>Iudah</hi> for <hi>Ioſiah;</hi> and no marvaile, for he was the <note n="f" place="margin">Lam. 4 20.</note> breath of their noſtrils, which being gone they periſhed. And are there not all theſe, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more conſiderations, to fill our ſoules with ſorrow, our eyes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:156167:17"/> with teares? <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 78.56.</note> How high is this God who is brought thus low amongſt us? <note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. 16 8. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Then, is he not our God by Covenant, to whom we have offered theſe indignities? Have not we a hand in his diſhonours? And is not our condition <note n="i" place="margin">2 Sam. 2.30.</note> involved in this? Is he not our ornament, to adorne us? our Tower, ſhield, wall of fire to keep us ſafe? Glory, crowne, to deck us? Is he diſhonoured, and can we be ſafe? <note n="k" place="margin">2 Chron. 22.11.</note> When <hi>Ioſiah</hi> heard the words of the Law, he rents his cloathes, as a teſtimony of his inward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternation and ſorrow: Why, what is the matter? Alas, God is diſhonoured, and the people in generall ingaged under Gods diſpleaſure for it; <note n="l" place="margin">2 Chron. 22.19, 20.</note> But ſee how kindly God takes at his hand this manifeſtation of his ſenſe of his diſhonour, and diſpleaſure; he gives the people a reſpiration, and him an exemption from the common ruine. <note n="m" place="margin">Ezek. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>Ezekiels mourners</hi> for the abominations of the time they lived in, are ſealed for ſafety. In a word, <note n="n" place="margin">Ioel 2.12.</note> the day cals for it; it is a day of mourning, of rending the heart with ſorrow, <note n="o" place="margin">1 Sam 7.6.</note> of drawing water, and pouring it out before the Lord: the ſins of our ſelves, and others require it, we may every where finde matter enough for ſorrow; the diſcovery of our affection to our God ingage us in it; the examples of the Saints invite us to it; the ſafety of ourſelves, and Kingdome cry loudly for it. <note n="p" place="margin">Plutarch. in Alexand.</note> 
               <hi>Alexanders</hi> Macedonians being ſenſible of his diſpleaſure, laid by their armes, put on their mourning at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, came running in troopes to his tent, where for almoſt three dayes ſpace they remained with loud cries, and abundance of teares, teſtifying their remorſe for offending him, beſeeching his pardon, which at laſt they gained. And <note n="q" place="margin">Guicciard. l. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Guicciardine</hi> tels us, That <hi>Lewis</hi> the twelfth of France, when he entred into <hi>Genoa,</hi> in his triumphant Chariot, with his ſword naked, reſolving to make a prey of their riches, and an example of many of the chiefe amongſt them, and to leave the reſt to his ſouldiers mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; But being met, firſt, by the chiefe; afterward, by the multitude, with great lamentation for their folly, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of teares, and cryes, as teſtimonies of their inward ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, his wrath was appeaſed towards them. Is there ſuch mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in men, and not more in God? O yes; he is the <note n="r" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.3.</note> originall and <note n="ſ" place="margin">Eph. 2.4.</note> ocean of it; it is his nature. The mother doth not with more earneſtneſſe deſire to be rid of her milke that fils her breaſts, nor give it forth with more delight to her <note n="t" place="margin">Mic. 7.18.</note> babe, then
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:156167:18"/> God his mercy. <note n="u" place="margin">Ezek. 18.31, 32.</note> He wooes men to accept it; he <note n="w" place="margin">Eſay 30.18.</note> waits that he may ſhew it; he takes any opportunity to extend it. <note n="x" place="margin">1 Iohn 1.<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Doe they confeſſe their ſins? then he forgives and covers. <note n="y" place="margin">Ier. 31.18, 19, 20.</note> Do they bewaile their folly? then he remits. <note n="z" place="margin">Hoſ. 14.4.</note> Doe they af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict their ſoules with the thought of what they have done? he will ſpeake peace. Doe they in earneſt mourne for thoſe indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities that have beene offered him? He will take the mourning garment from them, and give them for aſhes, beauty; for ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 61.3.</note> joy. And thus we ſee the ſecond meanes, whereby we may repaire Gods honour, and ſet him on high, in reſpect of our ſelves. But if you would have theſe former meanes to prove effectuall, you muſt adde to theſe a third, and that is</p>
            <p n="3">3. Reformation. An inward &amp; outward change. <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay 55.7.</hi> Tutius recurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quam male cu rere, crat Symbolum Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lippi tertii Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratoris. <hi>Reuſn. Symb.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let the wicked forſake his waies, and the ungodly man his thoughts;</hi> that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires. For a man to put on a forme of ſorrow, and ſelf dejecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; to cry to God for mercy on ſuch a day as this, and yet to hold faſt his God-diſhonouring wayes, what is this but to mock the Higheſt? Like <note n="c" place="margin">Philip. de Comm. Similiter fere &amp; Halverſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſes olim, &amp;c. <hi>Sabel l 7. Enn. 8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lewis</hi> the eleventh of France, who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a leaden crucifixe in his hat, and when he had done any act his conſcience checkt him for, he plucked off his hat and bowed to his Crucifixe, asking forgiveneſſe for it; hereby accounting himſelfe ſufficiently quitted from the guilt of his ſinne, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any more adoe. Juſt thus deale the moſt part of men with God; They ſinne, and they aske forgiveneſſe; whereby they think themſelves ſufficiently diſcharged of the old, and in caſe to begin on a new ſcore with him. Let us not deceive our ſelves, for <note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>God is not mocked;</hi> hee regards not ſhewes, but ſubſtance; not the face, but the heart; <note n="e" place="margin">Hoſ. 11.12. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Theogn. <hi>Sic &amp; dicit Deus.</hi>
               </note> nor cares hee for wording of it, it is deeds that he reſpects: <note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 1.16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>Ceaſe to doe evill, learne to doe well,</hi> elſe there is no treating with him. Hee may be angry with a people that <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 80.4.</note> 
               <hi>prayes;</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Eſay 50.8.</note> with a <hi>faſting,</hi> a <hi>weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> people; but when a people once cordially reformes, the <note n="i" place="margin">Ier. 18.8. Ionah 3.10.</note> quarrell is at an end. It is not the creature, but the ſinne God hates: the holding of it faſt, is the creatures ruine. <note n="k" place="margin">Iob 11.13, 14, 15.22.22. &amp;c. 1 Iohn 1.6.</note> But if this accurſed God-debaſing thing be once diſcarded, God takes poſſeſſion of his throne, mans ſoule, and all is <note n="l" place="margin">Eſay 32.17.</note> peace, and quietneſſe for ever. But now, becauſe in our ſelves we are not able to contribute ſo much as a <note n="m" place="margin">2 Cor. 3.5.</note> good thought towards this reformation, and advancing of God in our hearts, or actions,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:156167:18"/> but our ſufficiency is of God, <hi>Who</hi> 
               <note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Philip. 2.13.</hi> Non eſt devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis dediſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe totum, ſed fraudis deti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſen inimum. Proſp.</note> 
               <hi>workes both the will and the deed of his owne good pleaſure;</hi> therefore, we have need, not onely by prayer to ſeeke from his free mercy the pardon of thoſe indignities we have offered him heretofore, <note n="o" place="margin">Da quod ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, &amp; jube quod vis. Aug.</note> but for the future, ſtrength to enable us in this buſineſſe, that we may advance, and ſet up his glory in the world. Therefore let us earneſtly beſeech him; 1. That <note n="p" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.6.</note> he, who in the beginning cauſed light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, would vouchſafe to ſhine into our darke ſoules, to give the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Chriſt: for doubtleſſe, my brethren, this is a great cauſe, <note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Pet. 1.3.</hi> Claritas in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectu parit ardorem in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu.</note> why he is ſo low in our thoughts, feares, loves, ſervices in his Ordinances, Saints, Day, becauſe we are no more acquainted with him. For, did we but ſee what a glorious God he were, we would doubtleſſe more advance him in all. <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 68.1. &amp;c.</note> If God did but ariſe in our ſoules, then even as the ſunne drives away the darkeneſſe, and fogges that benight the earth, ſo would this light aboliſh the darke luſts of our ignorance, feares,<note n="s" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.14.</note> and prophaneneſſe of our ſpirits, which being rectified, would right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly order our outward man, and make us ſhine as lights in the midſt of a froward and perverſe generation; that others ſeeing the beames ſhining forth of this light within, may glorifie our Father which is in heaven. 2. <note n="t" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.5.</note> That God would likewiſe vouchſafe us a ſon like Spirit and affection to him; by ſhedding abroad his love in our hearts; whereby, as a ſonne is affected to honour his father, we may have our ſoules inlarged to glorifie him. If this were in us, 'twould make us like <note n="u" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>Horodot. Neh.</hi> 13.11.17.25.</note> 
               <hi>Croeſus</hi> dumbe ſonne to finde a tongue in his behalfe. <note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal. 34.3.139.21.22.</hi> Amantium mos eſt ut amorem ſuum ſilentiote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere nequeant. Chryſoſt.</note> There is nothing would more afflict us then his diſhonours, nor affect us then to ſee him advanced in the world. In truth this is a maine reaſon why men are no more ſenſible how it fares with his glory, or how much they diſhonour him, becauſe they looke at him as a God that is a ſtranger to them. I beſeech you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us more and more ſeeke after the knowledge of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to him, and the getting our hearts poſſeſt by this filiall diſpoſition, then we ſhall make it our buſineſſe, nay, 'twill be our meate and drinke to doe his will, to advance his glory, and lift up his name; <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 48.10.</note> that as his name is, ſo may be his eſteeme and praiſe amongſt the ſonnes of men. And thus you ſee as briefely as I could, the taske that lyes upon us all in generall, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:156167:19"/> the meanes whereby we may repaire our God in point of glory and honour in reſpect of our ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">2. We ſhould not thinke we have done our duties when we repaire Gods glory in reſpect of our ſelves; it is not here to be confined, but we muſt endeavour to ſpread his fame, and every one in our ſeverall ſpheares and places, to cauſe others to doe the ſame. Fathers, Maſters, <note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 25.27.</note> who are intruſted with the leaſt power, muſt put it forth for God; but eſpecially thoſe that are intruſted with greater abilitie and larger power, muſt not be wanting in it. And here give me leave I beſeech you, to uſe the liberty of Gods Embaſſador, and in his behalf to addreſſe my ſpeech to you, whom the Providence of God hath ſingled and called together, out of the many thouſands of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to doe his work, and advance his glory. Let me in a few words excite,<note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> and beſpeake you in his behalfe, to be zealous in this worke. Were it an imployment too low, I would hold my tongue; but is it not the worke of the eminenteſt Saints, the glorious Angels, nay of <note n="z" place="margin">Joh. 8.50.</note> Chriſt himſelfe? <note n="a" place="margin">Prov. 16.4.</note> Is it not the end for which God doth all he doth? Or were the iſſue of it ſhame, I might be ſilent; but when God ſayes it is honour, (as ſometimes amongſt the Romans the way to Honours Temple was through that of Vertue) it is argument ſufficient to perſwade brave mindes. <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 22.30.31.</note> Doe you not profeſſe your ſelves to be the ſonnes, the ſervants of this high God? whereby can you doe ſervice more then this, or teſtifie the truth of your relation you pretend? I <note n="d" place="margin">Magna faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora, magnis periculis emun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Dion. Hali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carn. l. <hi>9. Zach. 4.7.</hi>
               </note> confeſſe there are mountaines of oppoſition in your way, but is not this God of power ſufficient to make them plaine? Put caſe you ſuffer the loſſe of what you eſteeme of in it; is it not a <note n="e" place="margin">Refert Peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, non pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, non aurum &amp; lapides, ſed ſcutum divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam, fractam galeam, hebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem glad<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem vulner<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam cedere mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litibus ad orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum. Pet. Bleſſ.</note> ſcare of honour? and he ſufficient whoſe worke you doe, to make you amends? Suppoſe you undergoe as many reproaches, and wounds in your names as that Noble old <note n="f" place="margin">Plin. de<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> V<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. illuſt.</note> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>Marcus Manlius,</hi> did in his body in defence of the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toll; So many wounds, ſo many mouthes to proclaime your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and cry for heavens bleſſing on you and yours: and bee ſure, in Gods due time, <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 37.6.</note> 
               <hi>he will cleere your names, and make them like noone day, full of glory, and lustre.</hi> Is it in your eſtates? What loſt <hi>Ioſeph, Daniel, Nehemian,</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Amiſit prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſtum militis ordinem &amp; obtinuit dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatem Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratoriam, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Valentinian,</hi> and many others by this imployment? But yet put caſe you ſuffer; you can never by Gods Service be reall loſers;<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 19.29.</note> for if <hi>you part with wife, children,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:156167:19"/> houſe, or land,</hi> you ſhall gaine by the bargaine; in peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, joy of the holy Ghoſt, light of Gods countenance, &amp;c. <hi>here a hundred fold,</hi> and that is not all, the beſt is behind, <hi>in the end everlaſting life.</hi> Suppoſe it ſhould yet riſe higher, and might poſſibly coſt you your lives; you can never bring them to a better market, nor part with them in a more comfortable <note n="k" place="margin">Luke 17.33.</note> gainefull way then the advancement of Gods name, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring that he may be eſteemed, and ſerved like himſelfe. It is for your God, and can you doe too much, or be too zealous for ſuch a God as yours? There are foure ſorts of men, whoſe names are more illuſtrious, memory dearer, and themſelves more highly eſteemed, as perſons of greater deſert, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency amongſt the ſons of men then others be: <note n="a" place="margin">Bacon. Eſſay <hi>55.</hi>
               </note> Founders of States and Common-wealths, as <hi>Romulus, Cyrus, Caeſar, Ot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toman, &amp;c.</hi> or Law-givers, as <hi>Lycurgus, Solon, Iuſtinian, &amp;c.</hi> Saviours or deliverers from inteſtine wars, forraine ſervitude, &amp;c. ſo <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Caeſar, <hi>Veſpaſian, Aurelianus,</hi> &amp;c. or laſtly, ſuch as inlarge their territories, or make noble reſiſtance againſt invaders.</p>
            <p>Are theſe ſuch things as juſtly advance men in the opinion of the world? and is there not in theſe, and many more reſpects ſufficient in God, to excite the putting forth of your utmoſt abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities to ſet him on high? Were not our predeceſſors in former times like <note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Ezekiels</hi> miſerable infant, polluted with the filth of heatheniſh Paganiſme, and diſorderly Barbariſme? Who <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 17.26.</note> alotted them this good Land to dwell in? Who ſhaped, and framed them into goodly order, and comelineſſe, inſtead of a lawleſſe rout of Pagans, making us a Chriſtian Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; was it not He? Who deckt us with ſuch comely orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and jewels of Laws, and nationall Statutes, eſpecially with ſuch heavenly Ordinances, to be a light to our path, and a Lanthorne to our feet, to guide our ſoules in the way of life and peace? <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 147.19, 20.</note> doubtleſſe it was he. Who hath (in a word) kept hitherto our Land like <hi>Gideous</hi> fleece, drye, when the earth round about us in neighbour Countries hath beene wet with the blood of the ſlaine? who hath <note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 147.13. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrengthened the bars of our gates,</hi> preſerving us both from forraine invaſions, &amp; domeſtick treacheries; but He? We may truly ſay with <note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 124.2, 3.</note> Iſrael, <hi>If the Lord had not beene on our ſide when men roſe up againſt us, they had
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:156167:20"/> ſwallowed us up quick, &amp;c.</hi> And can you now doe too much for ſuch a God as this, to repaire his glory, and make his name high in this Land, where he ſo well deſerves it? If therefore you are reſolved (as I doubt not but you are) to ſet both ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the worke, then I beſeech you manifeſt it more and more,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By diſcountenancing, and puniſhing thoſe that daily bring him low, as ſoule-mouthed ſwearers, abominable blaſphemers, prophane Sabbath-breakers, lewd and wicked profeſſors, broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of errors; ignorant, hereticall, idle &amp; ſcandalous Miniſters; remiſſe or corrupt Magiſtrates; pleaders for <hi>Baal;</hi> perſecuters of Gods ſervants; &amp;, who ever they are that your Wiſdoms, regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Gods Word, ſhall diſcover to be enemies to the Crowne and dignity of this King of glory. Remember I beſeech you, 1. <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> You are Truſties in the behalfe of God; His providence hath called you together, and truſted you with power; part with your owne honour, ſo far as you may without deſtruction of the publicke intereſt, (I ſhall be far from perſwading you to write yours, like <hi>Dracoes</hi> Lawes, in blood) but not with Gods. I may ſay to you, as ſometimes <hi>Caeſar</hi> to his Ship-man in a te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt, Why feareſt thou? thou carrieſt Caeſar and his fortune; So, <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>1 Sam 15.24</hi> Fiat juſtitia, aut pereat mica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus. Erat Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolum Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandi primi Imperatoris. <hi>Reaſ. Symb.</hi>
               </note> why in the leaſt meaſure ſhould your Spirits reſiliate? is not the glory of the great God imbarqued in your managing of the affaires of Church and State? I beſeech you therefore be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited more and more to diſcharge this truſt. <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 101.8.</note> See how <hi>David</hi> ſets about the ridding the City of God from evill workers. <note n="k" place="margin">Ioſh. 7.11, 12</note> 
               <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> crying will not ſerve, nor faſting, till this be done. <note n="l" place="margin">1 King. 18.40</note> How zealous is <hi>Eliah</hi> for the Lord of Hoaſts in this reſpect? And <note n="m" place="margin">Exod. 32.26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> the meekeſt man alive, in recovering Gods glory by this meanes, is the hotteſt; like a flame of fire wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the midſt of ſtubble. Nature teaches us in point of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to be too ſenſible for our owne glory; I beſeech you be not leſſe for Gods, leſt by remiſneſſe you incurre the guilt of other ſins, and draw thereby upon your ſelves <note n="n" place="margin">1 King 20.12</note> a ſad account. 2. Are you not Truſties likewiſe in the behalfe of King and Kingdome? not onely intruſted with the Prerogative of the one, and the Liberties of the other, but Safety of them both? which how can that be firme ſo long as <note n="o" place="margin">Ioſh. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Achan</hi> is in the Camp; <note n="p" place="margin">Iona. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Ionah</hi> in the ſhip; <note n="q" place="margin">Iudg. 20.</note> and the men of Gibeah not diſcountenanced
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:156167:20"/> for their prophaneneſſe? but when <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 106.30.</note> 
               <hi>Phineas</hi> reale puts him upon this taske, the plague is ſtaid; and when the <note n="ſ" place="margin">Zach. 6.8.</note> Medes and Perſians do God right on the Chaldeans, Gods wrath is appeaſed.</p>
            <p>Then 2. for the future; I beſeech you bee carefull to fence Gods glory from being trampled on, and advance him in this Kingdome by wholeſome Laws; Bleſſed be God for thoſe we already enjoy; but give me leave to beſeech your moſt ſerious thoughts in this. For, doe you not each day finde in things that concerne our worldly welfare, wherein your predeceſſors might have done ſomething more, either in matter of <hi>expreſſion,</hi> or <hi>addition,</hi> then ere they did? I conceive in this I ſpeake of, you may finde the like: O, be a bleſſed meanes, that it may be mended. <note n="t" place="margin">Dan. 3.24.</note> Your Lawes for blaſpheming Gods name, let them be more ſevere; that this Land-deſtroying vice may be rooted out from amongſt us. Indeavour, that God may rule in his owne houſe, and be ſerved according as himſelfe requires, with a pure worſhip. That Ordinances may be like thoſe <note n="u" place="margin">Revel. 22.1.</note> Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall ſtreames without mud or mixture. That every Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick in this Land may be furniſhed with a burning, and ſhining light. That the waters of the <note n="w" place="margin">Ezek. 47.8, 9:</note> Sanctuary may flow thence plentifully, to make the fiſh live. That none may be choſen to ſerve in the Temple, but ſuch, <note n="x" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.9, 10. 2 Tim. 4.2.</note> who like the Arke, have <hi>Aarons</hi> Rod, the two Tables, and the pot of Manna in them. <note n="y" place="margin">Mal. 3.10.</note> That there may be meat in Gods houſe, <note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor 9.9.</note> and the mouth of the Oxe be not muzled that treadeth out the corne. <note n="a" place="margin">Neh. 13.17, &amp;c.</note> That the Lords Day may be obſerved with that devotion, and piety which he commands. That the name of <hi>Baal,</hi> and all falſe worſhip, may be rooted out from amongſt us. In a word; that whatſoever provokes the eyes of Gods glory may be extirpated. This is the way to ſet God on high, and to make us happy. But this cannot be, except God be pleaſed to ſhine on your counſels,<note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 18.21. 2 Sam. 23.3.</note> and bleſſe your indeavours, that by your meanes wee may enjoy yet one mercy more, and that is; 3. That the ſword of juſtice, and power to ſee the execution of theſe Lawes be committed into the hands of men fearing God: Such, who may reſemble in holineſſe that God whoſe place they ſupply, whoſe name they beare, and whoſe <note n="c" place="margin">2 Chro. 19.6.</note> judgement they execute: for, if they want piety, we cannot expect, but that they ſhould either bee ſenſleſſe of Gods diſhonours <note n="d" place="margin">Amos 6.12.</note>, or perhaps, which is worſe,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:156167:21"/> pervert Gods Ordinance, <note n="f" place="margin">Mic. 3.2, 3.</note> prove task-maſters to Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and diſcourage vertue.</p>
            <p>Thus I have made bold, according to my meaneneſſe, to preſent you with the way, whereby you may advance God in reſpect of others. And now to wind up this point: Are not the eyes of Chriſtendome upon you, to ſee what you will doe for your God? Is not one Kingdome in a very ſad plight, and doe not the foundations and pillars of this ſhake? Doe not the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Land caſt from all places, a pitifull-imploring eye upon you, to repaire their breaches, to ſettle their peace, and increaſe their happineſſe? Doth not the <note n="g" place="margin">Mic. 6.9.</note> rod of God which he ſhakes over the Land in peſtilence, and inteſtine diſſentions, cry loudly to you for reparation on this behalfe? and whereby may that be done, but by this meanes of a <note n="h" place="margin">Zeph. 2.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>timely,</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ier. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>cordiall,</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ezek. 18.30.</note> 
               <hi>univerſall</hi> reformation? This is the way to avert wrath; like <note n="l" place="margin">Manlii loc. com. p. <hi>142.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> ſometimes Biſhop of Magdenburge, againſt whom the Duke of Saxony raiſed an army; one comming from thence, the Duke asked him, what preparation the Biſhop made? he told him, that he ſaw none; Why, but (ſayes the Duke) what doth hee then? The other replied, That hee reformed his Church, his houſe his City; Which when the Duke heard, he disbanded his army, ſaying, He would never venture upon him that ingaged by ſuch a courſe God to aſſiſt him. Thus this courſe will make you <note n="m" place="margin">Eſay 58.8. &amp;c. 2 Chron. 15.2.</note> too hard for your enemies: it will hold up the hands and hearts of your friends, bee a continuall feaſt to your conſciences; <note n="n" place="margin">Eſay 38.3.</note> comfort your hearts on your death-beds; and cauſe: you with unſpeakeable joy one day to heare that <note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 25.21.</note> conſolation, Well done good and faithfull ſervants, enter you into your Maſters glory.</p>
            <p>And thus at the laſt I have finiſhed the firſt particular of my Text, Gods eminency; He is on high. In which, becauſe of my deſire to ſuit my diſcourſe to the day, I have beene the longer; therefore, I ſhall indeavour to make amends in the brevity of my diſcourſe upon the two branches of this firſt particular which remaine: wherein I ſhall rather point out, then proſecute; and with <note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 14.27</note> 
               <hi>Ionathan,</hi> rather give you a taſte, then a meale of the <hi>ſoule-quickning, minde-inlightning honey</hi> in this Text.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:156167:21"/>
            <p>This eminency of God (as you heard in the dividing of the text) is diſcovered, By
<list>
                  <item>1. The riſe and fountaine of it.</item>
                  <item>2. The eternity, and ſtability of it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Originall and fountaine of it, 'tis of, and from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he exalts himſelfe, ſaith the text. This is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in all the former reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Looke upon his eſſentiall eminency, and perfection, of holineſſe, life, power, &amp;c. All receive from his infinite fulneſſe, but how can he receive from any who is the <note n="q" place="margin">Revel. 1.8. Eſay 44.6. Pſal. 90.2.</note> firſt, in time eternally before them all; <note n="r" place="margin">Iob 22.2, 3. &amp;c.</note> and ſo perfect that no acceſſion or addition can be made to him by any creature in point of eſſentiall glory?</p>
            <p n="2">2. As for his throne, and glorious habitation, <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 102.25, 26.</note> his hands did frame, his fingers faſhioned it; not out of pre-exiſtent mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but from nothing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His glorious ſtate and dignity, he comes not by it as other Monarchs doe, by deſcent, choice, conqueſt, or the like; But well may he be Lord of that he <note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 1.1.</note> made; <note n="u" place="margin">Coloſ. 1.16.</note> His territories, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, whether in heaven, or earth, he gave a being to; and, by his all-powerfull wiſdome hath ſo contrived theſe things, that they ſubſiſt in him; nor can they, if they would, ſhake <note n="w" place="margin">Pſ. 103.19. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Orph.</note> off his government, they are ſo framed by him to be ſubſervient to it, and by his power ſo infinitely ſurpaſſing theirs, ſo led, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 66.7.</note> ſubdued, and ordered by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But doth not he <note n="y" place="margin">Eſay 43.20 21. Pſ. 148. <hi>per tot.</hi>
               </note> uſe the creatures in this great work to exalt himſelfe, and command them ſo to doe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. As <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob 35.6. &amp;c.</hi> Eminentiam Dei, praedicatur in ſcriptura.
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </note> for his eſſentiall glory, they cannot detract from, neither adde to that at all, it is above the ſpheare of their activity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It is true, in point of imployment he is pleaſed to ſet the creatures on work to advance the <hi>manifeſtation</hi> of his glory, and eminency, in the execution of many of his great works in the world: His Angels he imployes in <note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 4.13.10.20, 21.</note> governing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, <note n="b" place="margin">Revel. 7.2.8.6. &amp;c.</note> executing his decrees of judgement or mercy; His Miniſters are <note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1.</note> co-workers with him, in the converſion and ſalvation of ſoules, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But firſt, that he is pleaſed at all to uſe his creatures in ſuch affaires as may advance the manifeſtation of his eminency, is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:156167:22"/> a worke of <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 16.2. Zach. 4.6. Eſth. 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>dignation,</hi> and not of <hi>indigencie;</hi> in it he is pleaſed to put honour upon his creature, but is not neceſſitated in the leaſt meaſure to imploy it; for he is able to doe the ſame thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it if he pleaſe: He can give <note n="e" place="margin">Revel. 21.22.</note> light without the ſunne, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine without food, as in the kingdome of glory. Secondary cauſes indeed can doe nothing without him, but he doth in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, whatſoever he pleaſe, without them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it is his power whereby the creature workes: they firſt from him receiv'd it, as <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. 25.14.</hi> vide Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. de cauſa Dei mihi. p. <hi>165.</hi>
               </note> a ſtocke to trade with for his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. Pythag. citat. Juſt. Mart.</note> it is maintain'd by his continuall influence, and acted by him, whether it be in <note n="h" place="margin">1 Chron. 29.12.</note> nature, or in <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil. 2.</hi> Conatus noſtri nulli ſunt ſi non excitantur, &amp; incaſſi ſi non adjuvantur, Bern.</note> grace; ſo that although in ſome of his great workes he is pleaſed to cover his arme with the creatures ſhadow, yet ſtill, what ere is done, by <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſa.. 62.11.</hi> Multa facit in homine Deus quae non facit homo; nulla ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro facit homo, quae non facit Deus ut faciat homo, Aug. l. <hi>2.</hi> cont. <hi>2</hi> Epiſt. I clag. c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> power in this great buſineſſe, it is indeed Gods Worke.</p>
            <p>Therefore, ſeeing he exalts himſelfe, we ſhould learne in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing whereby the declarative highneſſe of this great God is advanced, to ſet the crown of glory upon his head; by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his hand in all, and giving him the praiſe. Alas, we are too apt (when either our ſelves are uſed, or elſe our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low creatures made Gods inſtruments, in a way of manifeſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to advance his highneſſe) ſo much to gaze on them, <note n="l" place="margin">Deut. 8.17. &amp;c. Hab. 1.16.</note> as here to terminate our fight, and goe no farther to behold that God whoſe inſtruments they were and by whoſe power what is done was brought to paſſe: And hence it is, that what is due to God, we give to them. The <hi>Romans</hi> had a cuſtome, that when they had received any great victory ore their enemie, <note n="m" place="margin">Laurumque ſuperbam Jn grem o Jovis ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciſſis deponere Poenis, &amp;c. Et taurum album Jovi macta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, &amp;c. Liv. l. <hi>6.</hi> Dec. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> the conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in his triumphant Chariot rode to the Capitoll, where in all humility he did preſent a Palme to Jupiter; therein acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging it was his power whereby this conqueſt was atchieved: You ſee that natures light did point, and prompt them to this duty, though they miſtooke the object where it was due. I would that we who doe pretend more light, did not expreſſe more darkeneſſe in this thing. It is reported, that <note n="n" place="margin">Manla Loc. com. p. <hi>178.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Adrian</hi> the fift being made Pope, the ſolemnitie at <hi>Lovain,</hi> where once he was head, being likewiſe kept, amongſt other papers hung up in the Hall, in one was written; <hi>Trajectum</hi> planted him, <hi>Lovain</hi> watered, <hi>Caeſar</hi> gave the increaſe: one wittily ſubſcribes, <hi>Hic Deus nihil fecit.</hi> And may we not under-write the ſame, if we ſpeake the conceptions of moſt mens inward thoughts? If God
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:156167:22"/> exalt his mercy in deliverances from common ruin, and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp;c. we talke of the Souldiers valour, the States mans Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie, but ſcarce one word of God. If he exalt his Juſtice in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, ſuppoſe in warre peſtilence, or the like; we ſpeake of the enemies in juſtice, crueltie, power; or the ayres corruption, earths infection, peoples diſtempers; thus, ſtill we are ſo lockt up in ſecond cauſes, as not to ſee the firſt; the <hi>covering</hi> doth ſo termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate our minds, we cannot ſee the <hi>Arme</hi> that workes all this.</p>
            <p>O let us be more wiſe, and learne to ſee our God in all his works; it will make us live more comfortably in all changes;<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 90.2.</note> not idolize our <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 115.1. 1 Chron. 29.114. &amp;c.</note> ſelves, or fellow creatures, but give him his due. Could we but with that bleſſed Saint behold the riſe of all from him, and how his power moves and acts in all, to carry them to the fountaine whence they iſſued, it would make us uſe his <note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 11.36.</note> doxologie, and give him the praiſe.</p>
            <p>And thus I have rather toucht then handled this firſt branch, whereby his eminencie is diſcovered, <hi>viz.</hi> The originall and fountaine of it. He exalts himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Gods eminencie is further diſcovered by <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: Sic <hi>Pſal. 102.12.</hi> R. Maymon. Morch. Nevoc. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> his eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie and immutabilitie, He ſits or dwells on high ſayes the text, and ſo <hi>Rabbi Maymony</hi> and other expoſitors underſtand the phraſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of <note n="b" place="margin">Eternitas, a parte ante, &amp; a parte poſt ei attribuitur, &amp;c</note> 
               <hi>eternity; Before the mountaines were brought forth, or ever the earth and the world were formed, even from everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting to everlaſting he is God.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay 43.10.</hi> Sine initio &amp; fine, vere &amp; ſemper idem, codem modo ſe habens ſolus eſt Deus, Iren. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>64.</hi>
               </note> There was none <hi>before</hi> him, neither ſhall any be <hi>after</hi> him, as the Prophet ſpeakes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In reſpect of <hi>Immutability,</hi> he is a high God, and <hi>dwels</hi> on high indeed, for <hi>he</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal. 3.6.</hi> Qua eſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex, Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, perfectiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus, Actus purus, &amp;c. vide Aquin. p. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>changes not:</hi> Nay, he is ſo farre from chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging in point of <hi>Eſſentiall eminencie,</hi> that there is not in him <note n="f" place="margin">James 1.17.</note> the <hi>leaſt ſhew, or ſhadow of it.</hi> 
               <note n="g" place="margin">Pſ. 102.26.27</note> Though both heaven and earth wax old as a garment, and as a veſture he doth change them, yet <hi>he indures for ever, his yeares have no end,</hi> there is his <hi>eternitie;</hi> and for all theſe changes he <hi>remaines the ſame,</hi> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeakes, there is his immutability. Indeede there is nothing but change in all things elſe: the Prophet <note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. 1.16.</note> 
               <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſees God on his throne, there he ſits, but under the throne are wheeles,<note n="i" place="margin">Dicimus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutabile bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num non eſſe niſi unum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Deum be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atum; ea vero quae fecit, bona quidem eſſe, quod ab illo; veruntamen mutabilia, quod non de illo, ſed de nihilo facta ſunt, <hi>Aug.</hi> l. <hi>12</hi> de Civ. Dei c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> and they are full of motion and revolution; there is, 1. the wheele of times and ſeaſons, <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen. 8.22.</hi> Temporalia ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit tempus, &amp;c. Aug.</note> 
               <hi>ſeede time and harvest, cold and heate, ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer and winter, day and night.</hi> Every thing under the ſunne hath
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:156167:23"/> its <note n="l" place="margin">Eccleſ. 3.1.</note> time and ſeaſon. Then 2. there is the wheele of <note n="m" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.4.</note> generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>One generation paſſeth away and another commeth,</hi> ſome dye, and others are borne, <note n="n" place="margin">Hieron. in verba Eccleſ. <hi>1 4.</hi> Tonſura ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neris humani. Senec.</note> even as in a wheele turning about, the part thou now ſeeſt, by and by is out of thy ſight; ſo ſaith <hi>Ierome,</hi> thoſe men, plants and other things which thou didſt even now ſee, are ſtraightway vaniſht, and others fill up their places which before appeared not. 3. There is the wheele of ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Looke upon bodies Politicke, what is become of thoſe foure <note n="o" place="margin">Zach. 6.1.</note> Monarchies that iſſued from between the brazen moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of Gods providence, are they not vaniſht? And may we not ſay the like of others too? Either their owne over-grown great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; or elſe ſome hand of violence hath deſtroy'd them; ſo that except in hiſtory we know not where to finde them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, to name no more; let us but caſt an eye upon our ſelves, and is not <hi>Iobs</hi> expreſſion [children of change] a title well befits us? How doe we change in all we are and have? From child-hood to youth, from youth to mans eſtate, from thence to age, <note n="p" place="margin">Job 14.2.</note> we never ſtand at a ſtay till duſt returnes to duſt. The face of heaven admits not of more changes then our mindes. As for our outward ſtate, how <note n="q" place="margin">In hoc vitae ſalo, circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantibus agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur procellis Roet. <hi>Job 1.</hi>
               </note> doth it change, and put on ſeverall ſhapes? to day in wealth, to morrow as poore as <hi>Iob:</hi> now on the throne, the next day on the pile like <note n="r" place="margin">Herodot. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Croeſus:</hi> to day in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reputation, to morrow like <hi>Belliſarius</hi> begging an almes of paſſengers: whether it be from good to bad, or contrary, it matters not, for ſtill it is change. Theſe changes are the wheeles of this High Gods <note n="s" place="margin">Rabbini apel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant creaturas Dei Mercavah. i. e. currum. Sic R. Maimon. Morch. Nevecb. l. <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. c. <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp; Alii.</note> Chariot in which he rides, and though he makes them all, yet he is the ſame. Though heaven and earth threaten to come together, though the waves roare, and waters lift up their voyce; though the thunder rattles and lightnings flye abroad; though men periſh and creatures be cut off as in the flood; yet as the ſunne, being above the place of ſtormes and tempeſts, goes on its courſe, and is not checkt by theſe; ſo is it far above the ſpheare of change, to make the leaſt <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 29.</note> mutation in this God. 1. <note n="u" place="margin">Gods repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is not changing.</note> And therefore if you read that he repents, doe not miſtake the phraſe: 'tis true; <note n="w" place="margin">Gen. 6.6. 1 Sam. 15.29. Numb. 23.19.</note> 'tis over man; but not as man, he doth it. In man it intimates a turbation of minde, a diſplicencie of the fact, a mutation of counſell, but in God 'tis not a change of counſell, but of fact; of things which are made by him, not of his preſcience; nor is it an alteration of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:156167:23"/> his nature, but a ſuſpenſion of his wrath, power, or ſome other attribute: he is a free agent, and whether he workes or no, it alters not himſelfe. 2. <note n="x" place="margin">Paſſions at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibuted to God doe not prove him mutable.</note> So if you reade that he is <note n="y" place="margin">Non ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum turbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis affectum; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum ultio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis effectum, &amp;c.</note> angry, jealous, or the like, then know, the Scripture being ordained for men, ſpeakes in their dialect; and as the nurſe in talking with her young one brings down her language to the childs conception, ſo God doth his; hence comes ſuch low expreſſions in holy writ, becauſe in ſpirituall things we are very dull, but yet we muſt not thinke that paſſions, or ſuch things are <note n="z" place="margin">Non in Deo eſt aliud quam juſta averſatio peccati, &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas majeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atis ſuae vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candae, &amp;c. <hi>Scalig.</hi>
               </note> really in God; but it is becauſe his workes are ſuch as mens when paſſions doe poſſeſſe their minds; as to deſtroy, conſume, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found, the worke he hath wrought, yet perturbations have no place in him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. So if <note n="a" place="margin">Comming or going, approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting, doe not prove God mutable in place.</note> you reade he comes, or goes, is abſent, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes, &amp;c. it is not by chance of place; that cannot be, for he is <note n="b" place="margin">Juſtin Mart. dial. cum Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phon.</note> 
               <hi>the place of all</hi> that hath a being; but it is <note n="c" place="margin">Non venit qui aberat, ſed apparet qui la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebat. Bern.</note> becauſe he that before to us was <hi>hid</hi> is now made manifeſt; the change is not in <hi>him,</hi> but in our ſight; our eyes are cured which before were blind, our minds unvaild. This <note n="d" place="margin">Divina fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenter viden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur occurrere atque praecur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere; &amp;c. Procl. l. de Anim.</note> 
               <hi>adaptation</hi> in us makes the change, there is none in him at all.</p>
            <p n="4">4. So if you reade he is ſometimes <hi>high,</hi> then <hi>low;</hi> doe not miſ underſtand: it is <hi>not in himſelfe,</hi> he is ſtill the ſame, but in the mindes of men, and eſtimation: now though blind eyes doe not behold the ſunne, and ſo its brightneſſe wants eſteeme from ſuch, it is nothing to the ſunne, they fare the worſe for it, and not that glorious lampe; ſo though all men ſhould diſ-eſteeme the Higheſt, nay, if they ſhould riſe up and fight againſt him, they may <note n="e" place="margin">Being High or Low in the world doe not prove God mutable in point of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie.</note> deprive themſelves of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by this courſe, but he is above their power, they <note n="f" place="margin">Job 35.8. &amp;c.</note> cannot reach him at all. And thus you ſee the ſtability of his glory.</p>
            <p>And now for the cloſe of all; you have had Gods <hi>eminencie</hi> diſcovered to you, both <hi>in it ſelfe,</hi> as alſo in reſpect of, 1. The <hi>Originall</hi> and <hi>fountaine</hi> of it, 2. The <hi>Eternity</hi> and <hi>Immutability</hi> of it: and why all this? Is it to fill our heads with notions; or to finde us matter for diſcourſe? No doubtleſſe, but that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>deepe impreſsions</hi> may be made upon our ſpirits, and we by it improved in point of practiſe. O that theſe notions might dwell upon our hearts and ſticke cloſe to our ſoules, and then I make no doubt, but we ſhould finde a <hi>changing,</hi> tranſ-forming
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:156167:24"/> power in them to effect theſe things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. This would take off our ſpirits from our too too fierce, and eager purſuite of earthly things. Alas, is it not a ſad ſight to ſee, that man one of Gods excellenteſt peeces, whom he hath created with an immortall ſoule, full of vaſte deſires, <note n="f" place="margin">Avaritia non ſuo, non alieno, non ipſo orbe contenta, totum poſſidet, &amp; de inopia queritur ſemper, Zen. Ser. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Avarit.</note> never to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied but with himſelfe, ſhould through the miſ-guidance of <note n="g" place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> 
               <hi>darke luſts,</hi> ſo farre miſtake his happineſſe, as <note n="h" place="margin">Jter ſine ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino. Pelagus ſine portu, &amp;c. Si Tarram amas, terra es; ſi Deum <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mas, quid vis ut di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam? Deus es. Aug.</note> to ſeeke it, in poore, empty, tranſient things? One runnes to riches as his <note n="i" place="margin">Prov. 10.15.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrong tower,</hi> which take the <note n="k" place="margin">Prov. 23.5.</note> wings of the Eagle and flye away: another ſeekes it in honours, and preferment, then which there is nothing more inconſtant, depending on mens eſteemes, who quickly change, either their <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 7.7, 8.</note> mindes, or <note n="m" place="margin">Pſa. 146.23.</note> lives, and ſo they come to be as firſt they were, nay perchance in far worſe condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for now their hearts being glew'd to theſe, when they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, it teares their ſoules in peeces, and farewell all content: thus they pay intereſt in their <note n="n" place="margin">Cum gravi dolore amittun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quae cum magno amore habentur, Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od. de ſum. bono.</note> griefes they have, for all the pleaſures which they found in theſe. Nay which is worſt of all, they doe not onely part with theſe (which in themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo full of change, had they but <note n="o" place="margin">Si bona mundi hujus peritura credimus, cur peritura tanto amore cupimus? Iſiod. ut ſup.</note> wiſedome to diſcerne it, they could expect no other) <note n="q" place="margin">Nitidi ſunt fores fulgore potentiae, interi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us tamen vacui ſunt elatione ſuperbiae. Iſiod. l. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>63.</hi>
               </note> but with their peace of conſcience, God, and all, whom they forſaking, loſe the <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 73.27. Phil. 3.19.</note> ſtableſt good, and by it ingulfe themſelves in miſery. Whereas did but their minds retaine the glory of this God we have ſpoken of, it would <note n="s" place="margin">Guſtavite &amp; eſurio, teti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtime &amp; exarſi in concupiſcentiam tuam. Aug. conf.</note> attract their ſpirits to himſelfe; it would make them cleave to him both in affection and <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 9.10.</note> dependencie; <note n="u" place="margin">Heb. 11.27.</note> it would make us feare to offend his Majeſtie; conſidering if he turne enemie <note n="w" place="margin">Jer. 17.4. Eſay 33.14.</note> there is not a worſe then he, who is not ſimply high, but laſts for aye to proſecute his foes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It would ſtirre up our ſoules to ſacrifice our <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 71.15.16.</note> ſtrength and beſt endeavours in his ſervice, we would never thinke wee <note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 104.31.33.34.</note> could too much ſerve a God, whoſe glory is ſo permanent, nor care what paines we tooke, or what we loſt for gaine of him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It would be a Well of life and comfort to us, to ſee that God is the ſame that ever he was. How have the Saints refreſht themſelves from this, when they have thought of former times <note n="z" place="margin">Da mihi te Domine. Aug. Omnis mihi copia quae Deus meus non eſt, egeſtas eſt, Aug. conf.</note>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:156167:24"/> in their diſtreſſe? how hath it <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 74.14.</note> 
               <hi>fed</hi> their ſpirits, and revived their ſoules, conſidering he is the ſame that did thoſe things? Therefore when they have ſeene what God hath done, their hearts <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 44.1.4. Pſal. 77.11.12. &amp;c.</note> are rais'd to expect the like againe; and ſo would ours, did we but take their courſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As the <note n="c" place="margin">Herodot. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aegyptians</hi> who live in the fens, being vext with gnats, they uſe to ſleepe in high towres, whereby thoſe creatures being not able to ſoare ſo high, they are delivered from the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them; ſo would it be with us, being bitten with earthly cares and feares; it would make us flye to God, and reſt in him, did we but <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 89.15. &amp;c. Pſal. 31.19. &amp;c. Pſal. 91.9. &amp;c.</note> know him as we ought to doe. We all complaine enough of cares and feares; Let us behold this God, and dwell in him, then they will vaniſh, and what ever come to paſſe, it will not much trouble us, if we finde <hi>All</hi> in <hi>One,</hi> whoſe glory is ſo great, and changes not.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
